<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Manassehs miraculous metamorphosis representing to euery sinne-loaden (if sinne-loathing) soule, 1 A conduit of consolation. 2 A comfort against desperation. 3 A con[du]ct to deuotion. A sermon preached before the thrice-famous Vniuersity of Cambridge, at Great Saint Maries, Septemb. 10. Anno Dom. 1620. By George Langford, Master of Arts, preacher of Gods Word, and chaplaine to the right honourable Thomas earle of Exceter.</title>
            <author>Langford, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15193A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106794</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842504</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842504</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7166</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7166)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 767:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Manassehs miraculous metamorphosis representing to euery sinne-loaden (if sinne-loathing) soule, 1 A conduit of consolation. 2 A comfort against desperation. 3 A con[du]ct to deuotion. A sermon preached before the thrice-famous Vniuersity of Cambridge, at Great Saint Maries, Septemb. 10. Anno Dom. 1620. By George Langford, Master of Arts, preacher of Gods Word, and chaplaine to the right honourable Thomas earle of Exceter.</title>
                  <author>Langford, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld for Iohn Clarke, and are to be sold at his shop vnder S. Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some print show-through, and some pages stained; title page stained, affecting two letters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7166:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7166:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MANASSEHS MIRACVLOVS METAMORPHOSIS:</p>
            <p>Repreſenting to euery <hi>Sinne-loaden</hi> (if <hi>Sinne-loathing</hi>) Soule,
<list>
                  <item>1 A <hi>Conduit</hi> of <hi>Conſolation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 A <hi>Comfort</hi> againſt <hi>Deſperation.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 A <hi>Cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ct</hi> to <hi>Deuotion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED BEFORE THE thrice-famous Vniuerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> at Great <hi>Saint Maries, Septemb.</hi> 10. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1620.</p>
            <p>By GEORGE LANGFORD, Maſter of Arts, Preacher of Gods Word, and Chaplaine to the Right Honourable THOMAS Earle of <hi>EXCETER.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MAT. 11.28.</bibl>
Come vnto mee all yee that labour and are heauy laden, and I will giue you reſt.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>LVKE 5.32.</bibl>
I come not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>AVGVST. in Pſal. 144.</bibl>
               <hi>Miſericordia Dei dat veniam peccatori, ſpem Juſtificationis, charitatem in qua omnia bona facias, dabit vitam aeternam, &amp; ſocietatem Angelorum.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>AVGVST. in Pſal. 130.</bibl>
               <hi>Debet vnuſquiſque noſtrum videre in quo profundo ſit, de quo clamet ad Dominum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Eld</hi> for <hi>Iohn Clarke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop vnder <hi>S. Peters</hi> Church in Cornhill. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7166:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7166:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE, and much Honored Knight, Sir <hi>Humphrey May,</hi> Chancelor of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Dutchy of <hi>Lancaſter G. L.</hi> wiſheth the <hi>confluence</hi> of all externall proſperity in this life, and the <hi>affluence</hi> of eternall Felicity in the life to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Bookes and Parchments long ſince fell into the hands of <hi>Carpus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.13.</note> what may I expect in this curious, this cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, this criticall, this <hi>carping</hi> age, but to be <hi>ſcoured</hi> &amp; <hi>ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> with the maleuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tongues of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> &amp; his mates? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Thucidides, lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Thucidides:</hi> Hearing and Reading haue a prerogatiue not to be liable to account; but Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Printing caſt themſelues vpon the racke of cenſure. For are there not in the popular ſort
<pb facs="tcp:7166:3"/>
as many <hi>heads</hi> as <hi>hearts? Quot capita tot ſententiae, quot homines tot humores, quot humores tot mores,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lipſius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lipſius.</note> The many headed multitude is ſo diuided into <hi>faction</hi> and <hi>action,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellua multorum capitum Seneca.</note> that <hi>Diogenes</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with all his Lanterne and candle-light, can ſcarce finde two in this noone-tide of the Goſpel, <hi>quibus vna vox aut votum, of one minde or mould.</hi> There were diuerſities of taſtes among <hi>Horaces</hi> gueſts, ſo that that which one deemed dainty, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnſauory to another. <hi>Dianaes Temple</hi> was burned by <hi>Heroſtratus</hi> the ſame night that <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the great was borne; One more nameleſſe then <hi>Heroſtratus</hi> ſaid: It was no maruell, for <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi> her ſelfe, protectreſſe of that ſacred Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was then abſent as midwife as ſo great a child-birth:<note place="margin">Cicero de natura Deorum, lib. <hi>2.</hi> Plutarch in Alexandro.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> commends this for a witty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; but <hi>Plutarch</hi> condemnes it at a witleſſe ieaſt. The like vnlike cenſures I looke for of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: for though the reuerend and learned pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence wherein I preached it, was not like <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> army,<note place="margin">Linius.</note> 
               <hi>Collunies omnium gentium,</hi> as <hi>Liuy</hi> cals it, a Miſcellany of all Nations; yet was it like S. <hi>Peters</hi> Audience, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. conſiſting of men of many Countries,<note place="margin">For it was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vpon Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge Faire Sunday.</note> and they (it may be) of contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Languages: <hi>Cato,</hi> me thought, called on me to plead for peace, <hi>Pompey</hi> for warre; the Souldiour cried, <hi>Arma virum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cane;</hi> the Merchant, <hi>Da pacem Domine:</hi> But I followed <hi>Ciceroes</hi> counſell, <hi>Seruiendum tempori,</hi> though <hi>Lentulus</hi> thought it the voice of fawning flatterie. But how? I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of <hi>Praier,</hi> which is not onely <hi>Medicina vulnerum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſtiles it, but is farre
<pb facs="tcp:7166:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
more ſoueraigne then the Phyſitians <hi>Catholicon,</hi> it is a medicine for all maladies. Were my Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Students in the abſtruſe myſteries of Arts &amp; Sciences? Behold, Prayer is their <hi>Oedipus</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue, to diſſolue their doubts. Were they Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants that traded for the Gold of Ophir? behold, Prayer ſanctifies their profits; hence <hi>Conſtantine</hi> writ a Prayer about his coyne. Were they manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Artificers, or ſuch as liued by retaile, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? behold, Prayer is, <hi>clauis diei, &amp;</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">It is not <hi>dura ſera,</hi> as <hi>Tibul.</hi> But <hi>firmaſera,</hi> as <hi>Ouid:</hi> Yea, <hi>ferrea ſera,</hi> as <hi>Plautus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſera no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis,</hi> it is the Key to open, and the Locke to ſhut vp their ſhops. In a word, were they<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 28.3.</note> bleſſed in the City, and bleſſed in the field? behold, Praier is their Embaſſador to praiſe their God, and giue him thankes.</p>
            <p>What then I ſpoke in the eare,<note place="margin">Quia lucem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam tenui huic &amp; per ſe obſcura ſcriptioni conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liare conatus ſum à luce veſtrâ: Lipſius, ad Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Conſul. &amp; Senat. Reip. Vltraiectinae.</note> I am bold to put vnder the ſhelter of your Honours protection, preſuming to winne ſome luſtre vnto this poore Paper-preſent, from your iudicious and learned Patronage. Your fidelitie in Court imploiments, your eminency in Natures endowments, haue moued God and the King to promote you, and all men to congratulate the amplification of your Fortunes. In your Honourable ſeate of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you are like the Philoſopher <hi>Zenocrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aelian. lib. <hi>13.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> into whoſe boſome the ſparrow fled from the tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of the Hawke: which doth aſcertaine me, that <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> after the Deluge of his teares, ſhall not be like <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue,<note place="margin">Gen. 8 9. <hi>Aelian.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> finding no place to reſt in, but that with <hi>Noah</hi> you will put forth your hand, and receiue him into the Arke of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting acceptance. Thus with <hi>Sinaetas</hi> in <hi>Aelian</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7166:4"/>
I preſume to preſent you with a fiſt-full of water, diſtilled from the Limbecke of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull ſoule:<note place="margin">Seneca de Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> or rather, with <hi>Aeſchines</hi> in <hi>Seneca,</hi> ſeeing I haue no meet preſent worthy ſo great a Perſon, I will gratifie you with my ſelfe, who will euer pray that your good <hi>name</hi> and <hi>fame</hi> MAY long <hi>flouriſh</hi> on earth,<note place="margin">Bonum nomen, bonum omen.</note> fenced and defended from the Theonine conſumption of Enuy,<note place="margin">Dente Theonino rodere, Horat.</note> till your conſummation in glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>this preſent <hi>Iune</hi> 4. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1621.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>At your Honors ſeruice I reſt euer in all duty deuoted,</hi> GEORGE LANGFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7166:4"/>
            <head>MANASSEHS MIRACVLOVS METAMORPHOSIS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 CHRON. 33.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Hee prayed to the Lord his God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is <hi>fathered</hi> vpon that ancient <hi>Father S. Ierome,</hi> that he was <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited</hi> before the Tribunall Seate of Gods Sacred Maieſtie, not for that hee was an excellent and eminent <hi>Enditer,</hi> or that his tongue was as the penne of a ſwift and ready writer (O let me admire theſe euer to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired gifts!) but, <hi>Quòd Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronianus, non Chriſtianus foret,</hi> for that hee was not ſo exact a Chriſtian, as an eloquent Ciceronian, too frequent in his <hi>Eſſe videatur.</hi> Therefore I call heauen and earth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that I come not this Holy day to hang golden Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels in the itching eares of any vaine-glorious Iſraelite,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.3.</note> ſuch as hee may plucke from himſelfe to make a molten Image. I deſire not <hi>Nazianzens</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> a <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> and flexible tongue, if by it he vnderſtand a <hi>defiled</hi> and flagitious tongue, euer ſpeaking <hi>ſonantia verba, ſed non ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantia,</hi> making a meere <hi>ſound,</hi> but neuer miniſtring any <hi>ſound</hi> comfort and conſolation. I cannot but deteſt Saint
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7166:5"/>
               <hi>Paules</hi> friuolous though fraudulent huckſters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Cor. 2.17.</hi> Cauponantes, Eraſmus, Beza. Adulterantes, Caluin.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſophiſticating, adulterating the Word of God: For, what other thing doe theſe chanting and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting Iuglers, theſe impotent and falſe Impoſters, then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſteale away the erring eyes of the ignorant; which frye are like <hi>Labans</hi> flocke, led by the eye, and violently poſted away to admiration. The ſiluer Trumpet of that Watch-man of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> carefully keeping <hi>Ward</hi> and ſcentinell in the houſe of his God,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ward</hi> of <hi>Ipſwich.</hi>
               </note> ſhould euer <hi>ſound</hi> ſhrilly in the eares of his brethren the ſonnes of <hi>Leui,</hi> who tels vs that this hyperbolicall kinde of teaching turneth <hi>ſound</hi> preaching into a <hi>ſound</hi> of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, <hi>tickling</hi> mens eares like a <hi>tinckling</hi> Cymball, feeding them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſpoyling the Plaine-Song with Deſcant and Diuiſion.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing ſtayed you a little in <hi>Atrio Templi,</hi> ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily let mee leade you <hi>in Sanctum Sanctorum.</hi> In this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Chapter,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.52.</note> 
               <hi>Ezra,</hi> Gods ſacred Secretary, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that Scribe taught vnto the Kingdom of heauen, ſummarily compriſeth, comprehendeth the Life and Death, the Acts and Monuments of thoſe two Kings of <hi>Iudah, Manaſſes</hi> and <hi>Amon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, hee blazeth <hi>Manaſſehs armes, Manaſſehs harmes:</hi> he points at him with an <hi>Ecce hominem.</hi> Behold the man: behold him falling and ſinning, behold him entangled in the ſnares of Satan, who is not vnfitly reſembled by the ancient Fathers to that mighty Hunter, that apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and rebellious <hi>Nimrod:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 10.9.</note> For hee hath not onely his <hi>hounds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. but alſo <hi>nets, ſnares, toyles,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſtiled them,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.7. 2 Tim. 2.26. Mat. 22.15. Marke 12.13.</note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. with both theſe, as once he laid for the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> ſo here he layes for <hi>Manaſſes:</hi> with his hounds, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they might take him; with his nets, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that they might entangle him; with both of them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ruthleſly they might murther his immortall ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.1.</note>The ſweet Singers of <hi>Iſrael</hi> may now ſit by the bankes of <hi>Babel,</hi> and poure out the cataracts of their compaſſion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7166:5"/>
empty the flood-gates of their affection vpon this <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the <hi>ſubiect</hi> of my Text. For, <hi>cecidit, cecidit Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes, Manaſſes</hi> hath caught a <hi>fall,</hi> Satan hath giuen him the <hi>foyle,</hi> both haue exceedingly bruis'd him:<note place="margin">Iob. 10.17.</note> changes and armies of ſorrowes are againſt him, the worme of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath ſtung him,<note place="margin">2 Cor: 12.7.</note> the meſſenger of Satan hath buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted him; Sinne,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> that euer arring and barking Bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound, whoſe teeth are as ſpeares, and whoſe iawes as ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, hath ceaz'd vpon him. In a word, hee hath tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Iericho,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 10.30.</note> from mount <hi>Zion</hi> to port <hi>Eſquiline,</hi> from the <hi>citie</hi> of God to the <hi>ſuburbs</hi> of hell, hee hath fallen among theeues, and is ſore wounded; <hi>cecidit, ah cecidit Manaſſes, Manaſſes</hi> is downe, but ſhall he riſe againe?</p>
            <p>Yes doubtleſſe, this downefall is not vnto death;<note place="margin">Iohn 11.4.</note> for as hee fell by ſinne, ſo did hee riſe by Repentance: as hee fell low into miſery, ſo did hee ſoare aloft to the ſeate of mercy. His fall was his riſe, hee fell to riſe: hee fell into priſon that hee might flye into Paradiſe. His fall was his riſe, hee fell to riſe, hee was a priſoner in <hi>Babylon,</hi> that hee might be a free Denizon in <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> happy, thrice-happy ſoules, <hi>Queis datur Elyſium ſic habitare nemus,</hi> who are thus enfranchized in the freedome of heauen.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe we then <hi>Manaſſes</hi> to be like bi-fronted <hi>Ianus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suppoſed to be <hi>Iapheth, Noahs</hi> eldeſt ſonne, who ſaw the ending of the old world, and the entrance of the new. Can: 5, 2, and 6, 8. 1 Tim: 3.15.</note> with two faces, the one looking toward <hi>Beth-auen,</hi> that ſink of ſin, the houſe of vanitie, the other beholding beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull <hi>Bethel,</hi> that houſe of God, the Church of the liuing God, <hi>Columba vnitatis, Can.</hi> 5. <hi>Columna veritatis,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. Chriſts Loue, his Doue, his vndefiled, the pillar &amp; ground of truth. For firſt, wee ſee <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſinning, and his ſinne wee ſee is aggrauated from the ſecond <hi>verſe</hi> vnto the 11. But as <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſinn'd, ſo <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſorrowed for ſinne, and hauing gone awhoring after other gods, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting his ſoule to ſacrilegious Idols, ſo he now acts the <hi>returne,</hi> takes the Rod into his owne hand, enioynes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a kind of Penance, he returnes to God by true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:7166:6"/>The which his repentance is here expreſſed by the three parts or members of it:
<list>
                  <item>1. By his <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of mouth.</item>
                  <item>2. By his <hi>Contrition</hi> of heart.</item>
                  <item>3. By his <hi>Conuerſion</hi> of the whole man.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>confeſſion</hi> is implied in that word, <hi>prayed:</hi> His <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition</hi> is implicitely enfolded in thoſe words, He <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> himſelfe. His <hi>conuerſion</hi> is brancht out into two ſeuerals: <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In terminum à quo:</hi> What he turned from.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In terminum ad quem,</hi> what he turned vnto.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the neere Neighbourhood, the coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that theſe words haue with the other! Now were it vſuall to giue names to Texts, this might not vnfitly be ſtiled, <hi>The Mirrour of Gods mercy in</hi> Manaſſehs <hi>miraculous Metamorphoſis;</hi> if you will, <hi>The Royall Exchange of the Merchant Royall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat: 13:46.</note> who hauing found a pearle of precious price, went and ſold all that he had, and bought it. Hee hath ſold his <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> to buy <hi>Piety;</hi> He hath ſold his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice,</hi> to buy <hi>Liberality:</hi> He hath ſold his <hi>Pride,</hi> to buy <hi>Humilitie;</hi> He hath ſold his <hi>Luxurie,</hi> to buy <hi>Frugality;</hi> he hath ſold his <hi>Crueltie,</hi> to buy <hi>Amity:</hi> In one word, he hath ſold all <hi>Iniquity,</hi> to buy a ſtate of <hi>Perpetuity,</hi> and being plunged in <hi>aduerſity,</hi> he ſends vp his <hi>perfume</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> to the God of <hi>Mercy,</hi> for ſo ſayes my Text; <hi>He prayed to the Lord his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen: 2.10.</note>Which like that Riuer of <hi>Eden, Gen.</hi> 2. may ſeeme to diuide it ſelfe into foure heads: 1. is an Agent. 2. is an Action. 3. is the Obiect of that Action. 4. is the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that Obiect.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Is an <hi>Agent, [He.]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Is an <hi>Action, [Prayed.]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Is the <hi>Obiect</hi> of that <hi>Action, [The Lord.]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. Is the <hi>Application</hi> of that <hi>Obiect, [His God.]</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>He,]</hi> an <hi>Agent. Prayed,]</hi> an <hi>Action. The Lord,]</hi> the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect</hi> of this <hi>Abiects prayer. His God,]</hi> The <hi>Application</hi> of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7166:6"/>
               <hi>Obiect,</hi> in the <hi>Supplication</hi> of this <hi>Abiect, who prayed to the Lord his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Welbeloued, in the Beſt-beloued Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, lend me your liſtning and attentiue eares, while of all theſe I ſpeake ſeuerally, though of ſome of them ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily: and firſt of the firſt part, namely the Agent, <hi>[He.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We need not now with the Eunuch aske any <hi>Philip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Agent. Acts 8:34.</note> 
               <hi>Of whom ſpeaketh the Prophet this, of himſelfe, or of ſome other man?</hi> this <hi>Capitall</hi> Sinners name, is writ in ſuch <hi>Capitall</hi> Letters, that hee that runnes may read it is <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> hee that did euill in the ſight of the Lord, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. It is <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> hee that went backe and built the hie places, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. It is <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> hee that built Altars in the houſe of the Lord, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. It is <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> he that cauſed his Sonnes to paſſe thorough the fire in the valley of <hi>Benhinnom:</hi> that gaue himſelfe to Witchcraft, and to charming; that did euill, yea, very much euill, that did euill in the ſight of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> and that to angel him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> one of Sins greateſt Aſſociates, one of Satans greateſt In-mates; an open opprobrious and fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitious ſinner; one who had drencht his ſoiled ſoule in the gall of vngodlineſſe,<note place="margin">Act. 8.23.</note> in the gall of bitterneſſe with <hi>Simon Magus:</hi> One, who Spider-like, out of his owne bowels had ſpun a faire threed, and weau'd the Web of vnrighteouſneſſe; it is <hi>ipſe,</hi> hee, hee it is that prayed: <hi>He prayed to the Lord his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A laſſe, fond deathling he, how durſt he vaile his guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, teare-drowned eyes to Heauen? how durſt his fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting knees and faultering feete approach before Gods aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſence? He <hi>prayed</hi> indeed, obſequiouſly he did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore for pardon, oh pardon, pardon mine outragious ſinnes: But why rather with <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.6.</note> was not his countenance changed, his thoughts troubled, the ioynts of his loynes looſed? why did not his knees knocke one againſt another, and his eyes fayle him for feare? Nature
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7166:7"/>
would deeme that in this deluge of diſtreſſe, he ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>prey</hi> vpon himſelfe, caſting his confuſed ſoule into the <hi>Chaos</hi> of horror, &amp; horrible confuſion, then <hi>pray</hi> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whoſe <hi>exoticall</hi> ſins ſo <hi>hideous,</hi> whoſe <hi>exorbitant</hi> ſins ſo <hi>hainous,</hi> might ſeeme to haue built a Babel of confuſion, to haue erected a wall of ſeperation 'twixt him &amp; his God. But <hi>ecce hominem,</hi> behold with attention, looke vpon <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> with admiration; he hath both forme &amp; beauty, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhall ſee him, you muſt needs deſire him, you muſt needs admire him! He is deſpiſed indeed &amp; neglected of himſelf, for he is a man full of ſorrowes, &amp; hath experience of infirmities;<note place="margin">Can. 1.5.</note> but regard yee him not becauſe he is black? becauſe the parching Sunnne of originall pollution, and the perpetration of actuall tranſgreſſion hath lookt vpon him?<note place="margin">Virgil Eglo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Alba liguſtra cadunt, vacinia nigra leguntur: Vzziah</hi> the Leper,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 26.19 Ier: 39.18.</note> though white as ſnow, ſhall be excluded the hoſte, when <hi>Ebed-melech</hi> the Blacke Moore, ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue one foote. For now behold <hi>Manaſſes</hi> (that Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent ſinner ſo ſuperlatiue) comming from Labanon, and looking from the Tower of Babylon,<note place="margin">Can: 4.8.</note> from the top of Amanah, Shener and Hermon, from the dens of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and from the mountaines of the Leopards. Behold him going about in the City,<note place="margin">Can: 3.2.</note> by the ſtreets and open pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſeeking him that his ſoule loueth, he ſought &amp; found him, or rather was found of him. For, which may ſtrike our ſenſes with aſtoniſhment, hee that ſuffered him to be led captiue, hath had compaſſion on him, he hath made a light to ſhine into the priſon, he that ſate in the ſhadow of death hath ſeene the Sun-ſhine of life. God hath appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him,<note place="margin">Acts 17.20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ipſa vita qua viuimus, quam viuimus,</hi> who is the life which we liue, by which wee liue. He, he ſmote <hi>Manaſſes</hi> on the ſide,<note place="margin">Acts 12.7.</note> as that deliuering Angell did bleſſed <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 2.4.5.</note> his chaines fell off, he raiſed him vp, he deliuered him out, he brought him into <hi>the wine cellar, and loue was his banner ouer him; he ſtaied him with flagons, and comforted him with apples, for he was ſicke of loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Can. 1.11.12.</note>Now therefore, ſeeing the <hi>winter</hi> of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> woe is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7166:7"/>
paſt, the raine is changed and is gone away, let his voyce like the voyce of a Turtle be heard in our eares.<note place="margin">Pliny nat: Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Turtur non canit ſed gemit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Plinie,</hi> the Turtle ſings not ſo much as ſighs,<note place="margin">Gen. 8.11. <hi>Ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e pacales Ouid.</hi> 2 Chron. 33.6. Mat. 2.9.</note> yet let <hi>Manaſſes</hi> be the Doue to bring an Oliue leafe, (true Embleme of trucefull peace) into the Arke of <hi>Noah.</hi> Let this ſtar-gazing Doctor be our <hi>condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour,</hi> leading vs like that ſtarre to the Babe at Bethlehem. Let him bee the meſſenger to bring theſe glad tidings of great ioy to all Repentants: That ſo endleſſe is the Ocean of Gods liberall mercie; ſo boundleſſe the ſea of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited bounty <hi>toward</hi> man, to (<hi>vntoward</hi> man,) that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect thrall, that enthralled obiect of miſerie, and ſubiect of all iniquitie, as that an impious and flagitious ſinner, may become a religious and repentant conuert, as that a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> may be <hi>Metamorphoſed;</hi> as that a Sonne of Satan, one of the broode of <hi>Belial,</hi> a brat of fathomleſſe perdition, may become a naturall ſonne of mother Sion, a ſacred Saint and Citizen of Ieruſalen, an heire apparent to the Kingdome, to the crowne of Heauen, inheriting eternall, aye-enduring beatitude and felicity. Well might the ſighfull Pſalmiſt ſo ſhrilly ſound that deuout, though dolefull ditty; <hi>Abyſſus abyſſum inuocat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.7.</note> 
               <hi>one deepe calleth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Pſal.</hi> 42. Well doth that worthy ſaying of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous worthy Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> ſuit and ſort it ſelfe with our preſent purpoſe, <hi>Abyſſus miſeriae inuocat abyſſum miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae,</hi> a deph of miſerie, cals for a depth of mercy: here Mercy and Miſerie are met together, Miſerie and Mercy, kindly doe kiſſe, embrace each other.</p>
            <p>Our God is not like Saint <hi>Baſils Magiſtrate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without the bowels of commiſerating compaſſion, of compaſſionate commiſeration:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 1, 6.9.</note> He loued thee <hi>Lo-am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi</hi> when thou waſt <hi>Lo-ruhamah;</hi> deſeruing nothing but deſertion, hee defer'd the ſentence of condemnation. When he diſplayes the bright beames of his <hi>Bounty,</hi> hee commeth forth as a Bridegrome out of his Chamber,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.5.</note> and reioyceth as a Gyant to runne his race: But ſpreading the Sable colours of his <hi>Seuerity,</hi> comming to write vs a Bill
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7166:8"/>
of <hi>Diuorcement,</hi> to giue the Deuill a <hi>Capeas Corpus,</hi> and <hi>Tophet</hi> an <hi>Habeas animam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suetonius in vita <hi>Neron.</hi> Clau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Caſ: Sect: <hi>10:</hi> quàm vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem neſure lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</note> oh then with <hi>Nero</hi> in <hi>Suetonius,</hi> he ſeemes to wiſh, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam, ò vtinam neſcirem literas,</hi> I would I had no cauſe to ſubſcribe to the execution of this Malefactor. With <hi>Bias</hi> that Iudge of Greece, hee neuer giues ſentence of death, but ſeemes to ſorrow. The Sword of his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> (vnlike to <hi>Ioabs</hi>) is willing to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſheath of his <hi>Mercy!</hi> Is he enforced to draw it? his bowels are rowled and turned within him: Is hee enforced to draw blood with it? himſelfe is wounded at the very heart.<note place="margin">Iſa: 1:24.</note> 
               <hi>He will eaſe him of his enemies, and auenge him of his aduerſaries. Eſa.</hi> 1. But it comes with a <hi>Sigh,</hi> with an <hi>Eheu, Ah,</hi> or <hi>Alas, I will eaſe me of thoſe that diſeaſe me: Exonerando me magis onero,</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes in another caſe, may the Lord vpon this occaſion, <hi>The puniſhing of Iſrael for his ſinne, addes ſorrow to the God of Iſrael: For alas, I muſt eaſe me of thoſe that diſpleaſe mee.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, O the inexhauſted treaſurie of Gods <hi>Mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom: 11:33.</hi> Fons vincit ſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entem, Auguſt.</note> the infinite Fountaine of his neuer-failing fauour, the head of whoſe euer-ſtreaming torrent, is more vnſearchable then that of <hi>Nilus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam: 23:15.</note> altogether paſt finding out. <hi>Oh that one would giue me to drinke of the water of the well of Beth-lehem,</hi> was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> deſire, but theſe Chryſtall Currents, this celeſtiall <hi>Nectar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 42.1. 1 Cor: 13.</note> is that my heart brayeth for, is that that my ſoule panteth after. Yet had I the tongue of Men and Angels, tipt with the choiceſt and chiefeſt luſtre of humane elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, I could not ſhadow in maske of words, or plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly portray with any pencill, this abundant, this euer-ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>torrent,</hi> this ſuper abundant, this ouer-ſtreaming <hi>Current</hi> of Gods <hi>Mercie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lift vp then thy head thou <hi>drooping</hi> ſoule, doe not <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire</hi> thou <hi>drouſie</hi> ſpirit, <hi>qui dilexit pollûtum, deſeret politum?</hi> Hee that <hi>loued Manaſſes wallowing</hi> in the blood of his ſons, can he <hi>loath</hi> thee <hi>waſht</hi> with the blood of his Sonne? from whoſe ſide iſſued thoſe two Sacramentall riuers, Blood and Water,<note place="margin">Ambroſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Luc.</note> 
               <hi>Aqua quae diluat, Sanquis qui redimat,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ambroſe: Water</hi> to clenſe thee, <hi>blood</hi> to redeeme
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7166:8"/>
thee. Haſt thou with <hi>Lot</hi> committed inceſt? Haſt thou with <hi>Dauid</hi> committed adulterie? Haſt thou with <hi>Peter</hi> denied Chriſt? Haſt thou with <hi>Paul</hi> perſecuted the Church? Haſt thou with <hi>Marcellinus</hi> ſacrificed to Idols? Yet wade not in the gulfe, walke not in the way of <hi>deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> this <hi>Almightie,</hi> this <hi>All-ſufficient</hi> Phyſitian, healed <hi>Lot</hi> of his <hi>Lethargie,</hi> deliuered <hi>Dauid</hi> from his <hi>Leproſie,</hi> purged <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Marcellinus</hi> for their ſhaking <hi>palſie,</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and recouered <hi>Paul</hi> out of his <hi>Apoplexie.</hi> He forgiues <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> aſwell as <hi>Hezekias,</hi> he forgiues a <hi>thouſand talents</hi> aſwell as <hi>one penie:</hi> He giues a <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Mercie</hi> as ſoone as <hi>one drop,</hi> he giues many <hi>Ephas</hi> as ſoone as one <hi>Omer. Decet magnum magna facere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquinas in Mat: <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> By this Almightie God, all mighty things are wrought, are brought to paſſe! He delights to blaze his bountie, which moſt appeares in great iniquitie; the Diamond ſhewes brighteſt on the blackeſt lead; Starres ſhine cleareſt in the darkeſt nights: Pearles ſhew rareſt on the baſeſt rings: ſo Gods bountie like the Diamond, his mercy like the Starre, his pitty like the Pearle, ſhewes brighteſt, ſhines cleareſt, ſeemes rareſt, on the blackeſt, on the darkeſt, on the baſeſt ſinner. God is more incomprehenſible in mercie, then it is poſſible thou canſt be in ſinning, the value of his bountie ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely ſurpaſſeth thine iniquitie!<note place="margin">Hierom.</note> Hence is it that Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> confidently affirmes, that <hi>Iudas</hi> ſinned more hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly in deſpairing of his Maſters <hi>pardon,</hi> then in betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Maſters <hi>perſon.</hi> His Maſter indeede is <hi>Sponſus ſanguinum</hi> as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſtiles him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bernard.</hi> Exod. 4:26.</note> a <hi>bloody husband</hi> as <hi>Zippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> called <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet a husband for vs, bloody for vs, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating here his contract, his eſpouſals; and hence his mariage, his ſacred Nuptials. Could he then cry with the Beleeuing thiefe, <hi>Domine memento mei, Lord remember me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 23:42.</note> then like that bleſſed thiefe he might ſteale the crowne, <hi>coeleſte furatur imperium</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> of the thiefe, hee took the Kingdome of heauen by violence.<note place="margin">Chryſ: Hom: <hi>2:</hi> de latr. Tanlerus: Med: cap. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> He came to the croſſe beſmear'd with the blood of others, but is waſht with the blood of Chriſt, and who then can deſpaire?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:7166:9"/>Who can deſpaire of pardon when he ſees his Sauiour triumphing vpon the Croſſe, bowing downe his head to kiſſe the ſinner, ſpreading abroad his armes to embrace the Prodigall?</p>
            <p>Who can deſpaire of pardon, when he doth remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that thoſe wolues who ſhed the heart-blood of the Lambe of God, ſhould be waſhed from their ſinnes by the blood that they ſhed?</p>
            <p>Who can deſpaire of pardon when he ſhall conſider, that where <hi>Adam</hi> was buried, there was <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified? as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> affirmeth.<note place="margin">Epiphan: apud Kemnit: de trad Jgnatius Epiſt: <hi>12.</hi> ad Roman. <hi>Can: 2:14.</hi> Bernard: in can. Ser: <hi>61.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> is crucified, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Ignatius, Ieſus my Loue, my life, is crucified, that in his wounds, the holes of the Rocke, the Doue may build her neſt;</hi> as ſweetly <hi>Bernard. Oh then ſuffer not the ſurging billowes, the ſtormy Euroclydons of deſpaire once to appal thy mind!</hi> Chriſts head was <hi>harrowed</hi> with thornes, that thine might be <hi>hallowed</hi> with the <hi>Diade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of glory. Chriſts face was beſmear'd with filthy <hi>ſpettle,</hi> that thine might <hi>ſhine</hi> brighter then the Sunne in his beauty. Chriſts eyes were <hi>darkned</hi> with the <hi>fogge</hi> of death, that thine might <hi>behold</hi> the Beatificall Viſion. Chriſts eares were fill'd with the <hi>ſcoffes</hi> of Satanicall malignity, that thine might be rauiſht with Angelicall Harmony. Chriſts lips were ſcornefully wet with macerating <hi>Vineger,</hi> that thine might carouſe the <hi>Nectar</hi> of <hi>Eternity.</hi> In Chriſts hand was claſped the <hi>Reed</hi> of reproach, that as a King thou mightſt ſway the <hi>Scepter</hi> of Felicity. Chriſts feet were nailed to the <hi>Foot-ſtoole</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> that thou mightſt trample on the powers of pitchy <hi>darkneſſe.</hi> In a word, Chriſts piercing <hi>inciſion,</hi> his bitter <hi>potion,</hi> his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable <hi>paſſion,</hi> his vnutterable <hi>compaſſion,</hi> his vnſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and vnſuppoſeable <hi>temptation, affliction, perſecution, proſecution,</hi> were all for thy ſake, that thou for his ſake ſhouldeſt ſhunne the dangerous ſhelfe and gulfe of deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.<note place="margin">Bern: in can: Serm: <hi>61:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quod ex te tibi deeſt, vſurpa ex viſceribus Domini,</hi> this was <hi>Bernards</hi> practiſe: Stand we in want of <hi>Mercy?</hi> let vs not bee wilfully wanting to our ſelues, in ſtanding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7166:9"/>
vpon our owne merit! workes of Supererrogation, are no ſmall derogation to Chriſts all-ſufficient ſatisfaction. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of condignitie (defended by the <hi>Cenuenticle of Trent</hi>) offer the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of Chriſt, a groſſe, a great indignity.<note place="margin">Concil. Trident. Se. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi> Erant haec duo non legitima chriſtianorum concilia, ſed ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannica Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſti conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula. Whitake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus de Synod. Florent. &amp; Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. <hi>Yet they call this</hi> Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima Trident. Synod. Poſſeuin. Biblioth. ſelect.</note> What incongruitie muſt there needes be, betweene our workes of congruitie, and the ſempiternall Crowne of felicitie? Surely no more proportion is there, then between <hi>Stillam muriae</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tullie.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; mare Aegaeum,</hi> betweene a drop of the ſea, and the maine Ocean. <hi>Pater terreſtris terreſtrem te generauit, regenerauit coeleſtis:</hi> Waſt thou <hi>defamed?</hi> yet then thy God <hi>aduanced</hi> thee. Waſt thou <hi>deformed?</hi> hee then <hi>reformed</hi> thee. Waſt thou quite <hi>degenerated?</hi> hee <hi>regenerates</hi> thee. <hi>Naſcimur homines, renaſcimur Chriſtiani:</hi> Wee are not borne Chriſtian, but brought to Chriſtianitie: yea, then oftentimes, when we perſecute that way vnto the death. Hath not God met vs in our iourney to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our ſelues out of <hi>breath,</hi> or <hi>breathing</hi> out ſlaughter againſt the Diſciples? Yes doubtleſſe, yet then, <hi>Et dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit bona ſua, &amp; condonauit mala tua,</hi> then did hee giue vs grace, and forgiue our graceleſſe aberrations. O tune not then the dolefull ditty of <hi>accurſed Cain,</hi> ſay not,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>My ſinne is greater then can be pardoned: Mentiris Cain, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> I dare giue thee the lie, for where Sinne aboundeth, there Grace ſuperaboundeth,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. Turne thy feete from <hi>Iudaſſes</hi> banefull Labarynth ſay not I haue ſinned and there <hi>ſtop,</hi> goe a ſtep further, I haue ſinned,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.4.</note> but with the Lord is <hi>Mercy; Pſa.</hi> 130. with the Lord is <hi>mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 130.</note> the <hi>Manna</hi> of the fainting ſoule; with the Lord is <hi>mercy,</hi> the Soueraigne ſalue to cure the ſore, the malady of <hi>Sinne:</hi> with the Lord is <hi>mercy;</hi> the <hi>Load-ſtone</hi> that drawes, the <hi>Load-ſtarre</hi> that conducts to life: This <hi>mercy</hi> hath <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> found; finding it, enioyes it; enioying it, enioynes thee neuer to deſpaire of boundleſſe <hi>mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, is the greatneſſe of Gods ineffable loue ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable? Is the graciouſneſſe of his ineſtimable boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo boundleſſe, ſo incomprehenſible, as to pardon a <hi>Manaſſes?</hi> a <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> one that had almoſt ſinn'd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonably,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 33.6.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:7166:10"/>
and like an vnskilfull, or rather wilfull Pilot, made ſhipwracke againſt the <hi>Rocke</hi> Chriſt Ieſus? Then heare my voice ye brood of <hi>Lamech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.23.</note> and hearken to my ſpeech ye Sonnes of <hi>Belial;</hi> you that for the leaſt diſgrace would ſlay a man in your wound, and for a puffe of wind a youngman in your hurt:<note place="margin">Gen. 49:6.</note> you that with <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui,</hi> in your wrath would ſlay a man, and in your rage digge downe a wall: O curſed, curſed be your wrath for it is fierce, and curſed, thrice curſed bee your rage, for it is cruell. The Lord doth ſit in heauen and laugh you to ſcorne, the higheſt God will haue you in diriſion: with <hi>Cain</hi> hee will make you vagabonds vpon the earth,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.2.</note> with <hi>Ioab</hi> hee will take you from the hornes of the Altar: hee will not ſuffer your hoare head to goe downe to the pit in peace, nor your gray hayres to the graue in plenty: for you haue put the bloud of warre vpon your girdles, and in your ſhooes the bloud of woe.</p>
            <p>But you my Brethren, beloued and longed for, my ioy and my crowne, into their ſecrets let not your ſoules come: my glory, be not you ioyned with their aſſemblies. Let Chriſts <hi>action</hi> be your <hi>inſtruction,</hi> though not for the <hi>equalitie</hi> of <hi>perfection,</hi> yet for the <hi>equitie</hi> of <hi>imitation.</hi> Doth <hi>Iudas</hi> come with a kiſſe (like a fawning foe) to betray him?<note place="margin">Mat: 26.50. Acts 2.</note> hee ſalutes him by the name of <hi>Friend, Mat.</hi> 26. He ſuffers the rayes of his <hi>compaſſion,</hi> radiantly to ſhine vpon thoſe, of whom hee ſuffered his <hi>Paſſion.</hi> Hee <hi>cures</hi> and recouers thoſe, of whom hee is <hi>wounded.</hi> Hee <hi>giues</hi> life to thoſe, who <hi>tooke</hi> life from him. Be followers then of God as deare Children; though men offend him, hee will ſeeke to ſaue them; though men worke miſchiefe, hee will ſeeke to winne them; though they turne aſide like a broken bow,<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.11.</note> hee will ſtriue to turne them; <hi>Turne you, turne you from your euill wayes: for why will yee dye yee houſe of Iſrael, Ezek.</hi> 33.11.</p>
            <p>And heare my voyce yee Tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> hearken to my words yee ſonnes of <hi>Aaron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 28.34.</note> Let your Bels be heard often, often your Pomegranates ſmelt; for hee that is a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:7166:10"/>
to day, a <hi>Saul,</hi> a <hi>Sheol,</hi> enlarging his deſire as hell; may be an <hi>Hezekias</hi> to morrow, a <hi>Paul, Paulus quaſi par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulus Chriſti,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> alludeth;<note place="margin">Auguſtin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> he that is a great one in the Kingdome of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> may at the leaſt become a little one in the Kingdome of <hi>happineſſe. Qui non eſt hodie, cras magis aptus erit:</hi> The <hi>Aegyptian Pyramides, Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſias Mauſolêum,</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> Capitoll were not perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in one day, nor was <hi>Zeuxis</hi> his <hi>Helena</hi> portraid with one Pencill. <hi>Ierichos</hi> wals muſt be compaſſed ſeuen daies,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 6.15.20.</note> yea ſeuen times the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th day, before they be leuel'd with the ground. Sleepy <hi>Samuel</hi> muſt three times be rooſed,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.10.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can ſay, <hi>Speake Lord, for thy Seruant heareth.</hi> Chriſt proceeds not to that <hi>cutting</hi> ſentence,<note place="margin">Luke 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Cut downe the fig-tree, Luk.</hi> 13. till three yeares hee had come and ſought fruit vpon it: which three yeares, were either thoſe of his Miniſterie; or as Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> expounds them,<note place="margin">Gregor. Homil: <hi>31.</hi> in Euangel. Theophylact. Baſil.</note> thoſe three times, <hi>Before</hi> the <hi>Law, Vnder</hi> the <hi>Law, After</hi> the <hi>Law.</hi> Or as <hi>Theophylact</hi> and S. <hi>Baſil</hi> do extend them, they are the three Ages of man; his <hi>Childhood</hi> which is a <hi>dream;</hi> his <hi>Youth,</hi> which is a <hi>Frenzy;</hi> his <hi>Old-age,</hi> which is a <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The <hi>Seruant</hi> is not better then his <hi>Master,</hi> nor is the <hi>Subiect</hi> aboue his <hi>Soueraigne;</hi> Let vs therefore follow him into his Vineyard, and three yeares ſeeke for fruit, though finding none we ſow in teares.<note place="margin">Iohn 5.4. Mat. 20.6.</note> Stay not to ſtep into this <hi>Betheſda,</hi> till an <hi>Angell</hi> doth ſtirre the water; <hi>Quîd ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis hîc otioſi?</hi> Goe worke to day in Gods Harueſt, though euen in it that enuious <hi>One</hi> hath ſowen his <hi>tares.</hi> Bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon inſtant; Giue attendance to reading and exhortation, to teaching and dehortation: Cry often, and cry aloud, lift vp your voyces like a <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet</hi> often, often ſhew the people their ſinnes, and the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> their tranſgreſſions; but as much as may bee, in reprouing, in reprehending, put on the bowels of tender <hi>Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many indeed, of whom I tell you weeping, doe giue their exhortations earneſtly, their redargutions vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but they omit that other, that <hi>vnum neceſſarium,</hi> to a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7166:11"/>
bruiſed ſoule,<note place="margin">Like thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, Reu. 8.</note> they deale not mercifully. One blowes his trumpet and fire followes; Another blowes his trumpet and haile enſues: A third is clothed with a cloud, and the raine-bow is on his head, he roares like a Lyon, and ſeuen thunders vtter their voice.</p>
            <p>That preiudiciall aiming at the perſons of men, too eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declares;<note place="margin">Leu. 10.1.</note> that our <hi>Nadabs</hi> and <hi>Abihus</hi> take not their fire from Gods altar. That <hi>pleading</hi> of iudgement, to the <hi>plunging</hi> of ſoules too deeply in the pit of <hi>deſperation,</hi> manifeſtly demonſtrats, that they care not to come in that <hi>ſtill voice,</hi> Kings 1.19.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 19.</note>But what ſhall we ſay to thoſe curſing <hi>Balaams,</hi> thoſe <hi>Bedlems</hi> of <hi>Babylon?</hi> to the ceremonies of terrour vſed by them at the time of <hi>Curſing?</hi> to their fierie torches? to their flaming candles caſt from on high, as though the fire of Gods furie was preſt and ready at their command? That <hi>Brand</hi> of hell Pope<note n="*" place="margin">This <hi>Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand</hi> had ſo much modeſtie as to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of his name, and would needs be called <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the ſeuenth.</note> 
               <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> whom for honors ſake here I mention euen as <hi>Pilate</hi> is in the Creed, this monſter as Cardinall <hi>Benno</hi> deſcribes him, was not more <hi>horrible</hi> in deluding the people with <note n="a" place="margin">Cùm vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, manicas ſuas diſcutiebat, &amp; in modum ſcintillarum ignis diſſiliebat. <hi>Card.</hi> Benno in vita Hildebr.</note> fire from his ſleeues, then are his ſucceſſors <hi>terrible</hi> in execrating thoſe, who refuſe to receiue the marke of the <note n="*" place="margin">Reu. 13.16.</note> 
               <hi>Beaſt</hi> in their right hands. All theſe are <hi>impoſtors,</hi> not <hi>paſtors;</hi> or if paſtors, not <hi>Dauids</hi> but <hi>Doegs,</hi> not <hi>Simon Peters</hi> but <hi>Simon Maguſſes,</hi> in the gall of bitterneſſe; not <hi>Alexanders</hi> but <hi>Ariuſſes, Aeriuſſes,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſebius Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Conſt.</hi> was a perſecuting Arrian heretick about the yeere of Chriſt 342.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebiuſſes,</hi> (of <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media</hi> not of <hi>Caeſaria,</hi>) ſhepheards they are that neuer whiſtle, but euer let looſe their dogs: ſhepheards they are that feed their ſheepe with <hi>wormewood,</hi> and make them drinke the water of <hi>gall: Paules</hi> milke is taken from the Lambes, his ſtronger meate from greater ſheepe:<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil. Eglog <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Et ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus pecori &amp; lac ſubducitur agnis, Menalcas</hi> complaint of falſe <hi>Damaetas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contrarily, let vs conſider, that<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> Miſcenda eſt lenitas ſeueritate, faciendumque quoddam ex vtraque temperamentum. Greg. Moral. lib. <hi>20.</hi> Seueritas exercenda eſt in peccata paucorum, &amp; (ſi quid minamur) cum dolore fiat. Auguſt. Epiſt. <hi>64.</hi> Diſcite ſubditorum matres vos eſſe debere, non dominos: ſtudete magis amari, quam metui.— matres fouendo, pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res vos corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendo exhibea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.—Suſpendite verbera, produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite vbera. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard. Super Can. Sermon. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Omnia remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, multa diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulo colligendae fraternitatis ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio, delictis (pluſquam opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet) remittendis penè ipſe delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo: vt fraternè de ſcipſo Cypria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>4</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Miniſter medicus eſt, is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7166:11"/>
curat vulnera non ipſe verberat,</hi> as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath it: we are Phyſitians for the ſoule, we muſt not wound, vnleſſe it be to heale.<note n="a" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Aqua guttatim lapſa lapidem cauat,</hi> by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent drops the ſtone is made <hi>hollow,</hi> and by feruent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions the <hi>hollow</hi> heart is made <hi>holy.</hi> The ſofter leade, not harder iron cuts the <hi>marble,</hi> and ſweeter phraſe, not harſher language doth ſometime peirce the ſtonier heart. Let vs therefore adde precept vnto precept, line vnto line, here a little and there a little, in mercy let vs exhort with iterations, compaſſionately let vs iterate our exhortations, <hi>Manaſſes</hi> is not dead but ſleepeth.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this reproueth our prying <hi>critickes</hi> our enuious <hi>Momes,</hi> our cenſorious<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 49.17.</note> 
               <hi>Dans, ſerpents</hi> by the way, &amp; <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> by the path, ſitting in iudgement, paſſing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing ſentence vpon euery notorious malefactor; a ſentence according to the<note n="c" place="margin">Dan. 6.8.</note> law of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which neuer altereth, neuer changeth. What would theſe men haue ſaid of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> had they ſeen him in the valley of <hi>Benhinnom,</hi> cauſing his ſons to paſſe throgh the fire vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Molech?</hi> What of the<note n="d" place="margin">Luke. 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>prodigall,</hi> had they ſeene him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his harlots, quaffing and carouſing, miſpending his goods vpon miſcreant varlots? What of<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 9.2.</note> Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> had they ſeene him in the high Prieſts houſe, deſiring let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Dimiſſorie to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> to perſecute the <hi>Diſciples?</hi> What of Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> had they ſeene him addicted to gluttonie<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13.13.</note> and drunkennes, to chambering and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to ſtrife and enuying? Surely they would haue caſt them vpon the <hi>racke</hi> of cenſure, daſht them againſt the <hi>rocke</hi> of <hi>deſpaire,</hi> and excluded them from any hope of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture amendment, of fruitfull recouerie.</p>
            <p>Could <hi>Manaſſes</hi> haue diſrob'd himſelfe of his robes of royaltie, and conſulted with ſome cenſurer as <hi>Saul</hi> with the witch at <hi>En-dor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 28.8. <hi>Irenaeus aduerſ. Haereſ. lib</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> asking him as <hi>Marcion</hi> did <hi>Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, Agnoſcis nos?</hi> doeſt thou know who I am? Doubtles he would haue anſwered him as roundly (though not as truly) as <hi>Polycarpus</hi> did <hi>Marcion, Agnoſco primogenitum Satanae,</hi> I know thee to be the firſtling like the firſt borne
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7166:12"/>
ſonne of Satan: but blind had beene their cenſure of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie, and euer, ô euer, may ſuch <hi>falt-finding</hi> carpers, ſuch <hi>falt-minding</hi> and cenſorious cauillers be deceiued. Let vs not then curiouſly pry into the <hi>ſacred</hi> Arke of Gods <hi>ſecret</hi> predeſtination, let it ſuffice vs that we are of Gods <hi>Court,</hi> though not of his <hi>counſell,</hi> for I ſay to euerie one that is among you, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that no man preſume to vnderſtand aboue that which is meete to vnderſtand, but that he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand according to ſobrietie. We may pronounce of the barren figge-tree, that it hath no fruit growing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.19.</note> but onely Chriſt may ſay, <hi>cut it downe,</hi> or <hi>neuer fruit grow on thee henceforward.</hi> For God hath left euen in the wicked, ſome reliques and remainders of his image, like the rootes of <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> tree;<note place="margin">Dan. 4 11.12.</note> ſome <hi>ſtampes</hi> thereof are yet to be found, euen in nature vnregenerate, like the <hi>stumps</hi> of <hi>Dagons</hi> hands,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.4.</note> which like <hi>Iobs</hi> meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, may bring theſe ſad tidings of great wo, we only are eſcaped alone to tell thee, that we are the ruins of a ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous edifice. True it is, that <hi>Adam</hi> by his fall did bruiſe this image, ſo that now we may make that <hi>Quaeri</hi> with our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe image and ſuperſcription is this?</hi> but yet the breaking thereof is not like that of <hi>Ieremies bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, Ier.</hi> 19. broken it is not like a potters veſſell,<note place="margin">Ier. 19.10.11</note> that can neuer be made whole againe. Hee that had giuen Satan an <hi>Indenture</hi> as a <hi>ceiſure</hi> of his ſoule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M. Foxe</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrolog. Iunii vita.</note> at the requeſt of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> was ſet free againe. <hi>Iunius</hi> was once an irreligious <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> yet after writ <hi>Diuinely</hi> of the <hi>Deitie.</hi> Heroicall <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> was once a ſuperſtitious Frier, <hi>enueloped</hi> in the cloud, <hi>enuironed</hi> in the fogge of Egyptian, of papall and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble darkeneſſe, yet after became a champion, marching couragiouſly againſt that Hydra-headed monſter, lurking in that ſepti-montiall<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>This</hi> Septi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montiall <hi>Citie is Rome, that ſeat of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> Reu. <hi>17.9. which hath ſeuen hils:</hi> Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temque vna ſibi muro circundidit arces. Virgil. Georgie. lib. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; Aeneid. lib. <hi>6.</hi> Septem vrbs alta iugis, toti quae praeſidet orbi. propert. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Eleg. <hi>10.</hi> Eutropius, Victor, <hi>with diuers others do name theſe ſeuen hills. they are thus called,</hi> Palatinus, Capitolinus, Auentinus, Eſquilinus, Caeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinalis, <hi>and</hi> Viminalis. Eutrop. Hiſt. Publ. Vict. in Deſcript. vrbis Rom.</note> Citie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7166:12"/>Which firſt meets with our cold friends that gad and go aſtray to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> with the <hi>vniuſt</hi> iudgement, of the <hi>Ouer-iuſt</hi> ſect of our blacke mouth'd <hi>Browniſts,</hi> our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Nouatians, Luciferians, Donatists, Seperatiſts:</hi> Theſe vpon a ſuppoſall that our mother is <hi>blacke,</hi> thinke that for euer ſhe hath loſt her <hi>beauty.</hi> They cry out with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we would haue cured <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 51.9.</note> when as <hi>England</hi> may twit them with <hi>Iſraels</hi> prouerbe, <hi>Phyſition, heale thy ſelfe.</hi> Their <hi>ingredients</hi> are vehement <hi>purgers;</hi> the <hi>vomit</hi> they haue preſcribed, will <hi>caſt</hi> vs out of the Church, if once admitted, if once adminiſtred: Their <hi>colloquintida, vertit amorem in amarorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> as ſpeakes Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> it hath turn'd their loue into lowring, and makes vs cry out, <hi>Mors in olla,</hi> death is in the pot, is in the potion.<note place="margin">2 Kings 4.40.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is remarkable that their firſt <hi>founder Browne,</hi> hath <hi>found</hi> the way into our Church againe: euen hee that held wee had no Church in <hi>England,</hi> is now Paſtor at a place called<note n="*" place="margin">A Towne in Northampton ſhire.</note> 
               <hi>A church: Bonum nomen, bonum omen, At quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum mutat us ab illo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sed hinc illae lachrymae,</hi> Wee need not ſaile to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> to find out incenſed &amp; cenſorious foes for our Church of <hi>England,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, It is thou my Adopted ſonne, ſayes our Mother Zion, my companion, my guide and familiar, which delighted in conſulting together, and went into the houſe of God as companions: It is thou my familiar, whom I truſted, which did eate of my <hi>bread,</hi> and ſucke of my <hi>breſts,</hi> thou haſt lifted vp thy heele againſt mee.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not here of <hi>Heretikes,</hi> thoſe foxes, <hi>qui conantur corrumpere fidem,</hi> but of <hi>Schiſmatikes,</hi> thoſe crafty cubs, thoſe ſharpe-phanged Satyriſts,<note n="a" place="margin">Non verenda retego, ſed inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recunda refuto: vtinam nobis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquerint moder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Noe, vnde à nobis poſſent ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatenus operiri, Bernard Epiſt. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui conantur diſrumpere charitatem.</hi> Such theſe are, as<note n="b" place="margin">Leo ad Paleaſt.</note> 
               <hi>Leo</hi> ſpeakes of, <hi>Eccleſiae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tenent, &amp; contra Eccleſiam dimicant:</hi> Such theſe are as <note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. de Ciu. Dei, lib. <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> aymes at, <hi>qui ſub vocabulo Chriſtiano, doctrinae,</hi> I may ſay <hi>diſciplinae reſiſterent Chriſtianae.</hi> Furious vapours they are, who being reſtrained ſhake the very earth for vent. Such were the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> ſuch are the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> ſuch are the <hi>Anticonformiſts</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:7166:13"/>
who threatned to introduce their <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> that <hi>Troian horſe,</hi> not as the <hi>Grecians</hi> with <hi>quaffing</hi> and <hi>feaſting,</hi> but as the <hi>Germanes</hi> with <hi>quarreling</hi> and <hi>fiſting.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex Bullinger. Vdal. Penri.</note> So poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt are they with an ouer-weening conceit of their owne worthleſſe worthineſſe, as that they dare condemne the preſent <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as groſſely idolatrous; but <hi>Pigmaleon-like</hi> they fall in loue with an Image of their owne <hi>caruing,</hi> for needes will they be their owne <hi>caruers.</hi> Not vnlike are theſe vnto thoſe of whom <note n="e" place="margin">Iren Aduerſ. Heraeſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> writeth, who were ſo beſotted with an opinion of themſelues, that they accounted their owne writings to be <hi>Goſpels:</hi> like they are vnto the<note n="f" place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> 
               <hi>Manicheis,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued their name of <hi>Manna,</hi> as if <hi>Manna-like</hi> their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine had come from heauen: or like thoſe who tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their Sectaries<note n="g" place="margin">Haeretici qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſic dicti ob inſignem eruditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem quam ſibi vendicabant: Hen. Stephan. contra quos Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, accounted themſelues to be ignorant of nothing.</p>
            <p>Yet our chiefeſt <hi>Sectaries</hi> ſo <hi>cenſorious</hi> of vs, cannot fully agree in the maine points of erecting this their <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> Maſter <hi>Knox</hi> and others compiled a Booke of Diſcipline after the <hi>Geneua</hi> faſhion, but it was reiected of the <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinarians,</hi> and tauntingly tearmed, <hi>A deuout Imagination.</hi> Another Booke called<note n="*" place="margin">About 1587.</note> 
               <hi>Diſciplina Eccleſiae ſacra, verbo Dei deſcripta,</hi> was yet by them corrected, altered, and amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; ſo that this tumult is like that which <hi>Demetrius</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. wherein the moſt part know not wherefore they be come together.</p>
            <p>Some, when <hi>ambitiouſly</hi> they cannot exalt themſelues, grow moſſe-growne in <hi>Schiſme. Arrius</hi> coueting the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke of <hi>Alexandria, Donatus</hi> the Biſhopricke of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage, Nouatus</hi> a Biſhopricke in <hi>Italy,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes this to <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> for a Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, in that hee held, <hi>Pre byſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ab Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po nulla diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia debere diſcerni.</hi> And <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith that this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>ſtultitiae plena: Epiphan. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Heraeſ.</hi> 75.</note> 
               <hi>Aerius</hi> a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke in <hi>Pontus;</hi> all theſe repulſed, grew turbulently <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious</hi> againſt the Senators of <hi>Sion.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Sir <hi>George Paul</hi> in the life of <hi>Iohn Whitgift</hi> Lord ArchBi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury. p. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Cartwrights</hi> firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment grew from that, for that hee was neyther <hi>regarded</hi> nor <hi>rewarded</hi> by Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for his Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demicall diſputation, correſpondently to his expectation.</p>
            <p>Another banefull ſeede of <hi>cenſorious</hi> Schiſmatickes is <hi>Auarice.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Theod. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus</hi> fell into Schiſmes, being
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7166:13"/>
allured with <hi>preferment,</hi> which hee expected of <hi>Zenobia</hi> the Queene of <hi>Arabia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoret. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> And why doe ſo many affect the <hi>Geneua Diſcipline,</hi> but to fill their greedy mawes with the ruines of <hi>Cathedrall</hi> Churches?</p>
            <p>But aboue all, the contempt of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Authoritie,</hi> is the greateſt breeder of this Schiſmaticall antipathie. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Cypr. ad Pupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum.</note> 
               <hi>Schiſmata &amp; Haereſes ortae ſunt, niſi dum Epiſcopus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perba praeſumptione quorundam contemnitur?</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Cyprian.</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Hieron. cont. Luciferian.</note> If <hi>Biſhops</hi> had not this authoritie, <hi>tot in Eccleſiis effice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur Schiſmata, quot Sacerdotes,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Ierome.</hi> All the ancient authenticke <hi>Fathers</hi> beleeued that the calling of <hi>Biſhops</hi> was <hi>Iure Apoſtolico.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iren. contra Haereſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> cals this, <hi>The ancient Tradition of the Apoſtles thorough the whole world.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Cyprian. lib. <hi>4.</hi> epiſt. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> ſayes, that the <hi>Biſhop is honoured by the acceptance of God.</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>33.</hi> in Act. <hi>15.</hi> Hieron. de ſcript. Eccleſ. Ambr. in Gal. <hi>1.</hi> Aug. cont. Creſcon. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Iames</hi> the Apoſtle was <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſaith <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome. Saint</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Gregr. lib. <hi>6.</hi> epiſt. <hi>37.</hi> Euſ. Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi> Hier. ad Euagr.</note> 
               <hi>Marke</hi> the Euangeliſt was <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Orig. hom. <hi>6.</hi> in Lucam. Hieron. deſcript. Eccleſ. in Ignat. Bellar. de Rom. Pont. l. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Saint Peter</hi> was <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Origen.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Cypr. Epiſt. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> teacheth vs, that a <hi>Biſhopricke</hi> is an <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> and an <hi>Apoſtleſhip</hi> a <hi>Biſhopricke.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. <hi>44.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> expounding that in the forty fourth <hi>Pſalme, Inſtead of thy fathers thou ſhalt haue children,</hi> ſhewes, that <hi>our Biſhops in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited the Apoſtles, as children their fathers.</hi> Who then not tranſported with preiudice, dare <hi>cenſoriouſly</hi> traduce this tradition Apoſtolicke? who not violently <hi>cenſorious</hi> would ſay with<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. contra Abail. epiſt.</hi> 190. Thus you ſee by all conſent of authenticke Antiquitie, that <hi>Biſhops</hi> (whom our Noueliſts <hi>cenſure</hi> as limbes of Antichriſt,) are ordained by diuine inſtitution, and Apoſtolicke tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Indeede <hi>Ierome</hi> ſayes that <hi>Biſhops</hi> are greater then Prieſts, rather by the cuſtome of men, then by the conſtitution of God. But 1. this is the priuate opinion of <hi>S. Ierome.</hi> 2. He was no great friend to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> becauſe he ſhould haue beene elected <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> but by reaſon of his emulators had the repulſe. 3. He ſaith <hi>Biſhops</hi> were ſet ouer the Church when thoſe Schiſmes beganne, <hi>I hold of Paul, I of Apollos, I of Cephas. Comment. in Tit.</hi> 1. But did not this fall out in the Apoſtles daies? 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 1.12. 4 Hee ſo magnified his Prieſthood, to quell the pride of diuers inſolent Deacons, who compared themſelues with Prieſts. 5. He in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry places of his writings declares himſelfe againſt the paritie of Miniſters, as <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contr. Iouinian. Jn comment. in Eſa.</hi> 19. <hi>in Ier.</hi> 6. <hi>In Epiſt. ad Ruſticum Monachum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Abailardus, Omnes Patres ſic, at ego non ſic?</hi> the <hi>tyde</hi> of opinion ſeemes to <hi>glide</hi> that way, but wee affect to <hi>ſtriue</hi> againſt the <hi>ſtreame,</hi> and <hi>extreamely</hi> to croſſe the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Antiquitie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:7166:14"/>As theſe are thus troubled with a ſwelling <hi>ſpleene,</hi> ſo our Enemies at <hi>Rome</hi> are much moleſted with an ouerflowing <hi>gall.</hi> Theſe <hi>Catilines</hi> thinke our caſe deſperate, that there is no <hi>Roome</hi> for vs, no manſions in our Fathers houſe. Hence is it, that their great <hi>Cham</hi> the Pope, (worſhipt might hee be) vpon the Euening before <hi>Good-friday,</hi> in great ſolemnitie <hi>curſeth</hi> vs all to hell, whereas<note n="*" place="margin">In one of the praiers appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy for <hi>Good-friday.</hi> Ier. 8.22.</note> we for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence the next day, <hi>pray</hi> for the conuerſion and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him and his as being <hi>Heretikes.</hi> But is there no Balme at <hi>Gilead,</hi> to recouer the health of the daughter of <hi>England?</hi> What <hi>Scythian</hi> cruelty is this, to deny that to <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which they grant to meere <hi>Pagans?</hi> Doth not their <hi>Leaden-Legend</hi> report (<hi>fides ſit penes Authorem,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it who liſt,) that the ſoules of<note n="a" place="margin">This former fable is to bee ſeen in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations of S. <hi>Bridgit:</hi> A book allowed by the Pope: And <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus Cia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onus</hi> a Spaniſh Frier hath defended this opinion.</note> 
               <hi>Traianus</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Damaſcen <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates both theſe Lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.</hi> Damaſc. orat de defunct. <hi>but hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes,</hi> At nos definimus nihil, tantum fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſtudio rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocinamur.</note> 
               <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conella</hi> were both of them reſcued from hell, tranſported into <hi>Abrahams boſome,</hi> the one at the praiers of<note n="c" place="margin">Did God euer the like?</note> Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> the other of <hi>Tecla?</hi> And may not much more <hi>flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> ſinners (ſuppoſe wee were ſuch) become <hi>religious</hi> Conuerts?</p>
            <p>But ſurely, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> malignancy would <hi>extenuate</hi> our ſickneſſe, would wee <hi>exenterate</hi> our Mother and change the ayre: but alas, the infection is there too groſſe, nor could it be any better then a furious phrenſie, to reſort to that <hi>Romiſh Mountebancke,</hi> hauing at home ſuch approu'd <hi>Phyſitians.</hi> And be it that they may boaſt of their <hi>Aër,</hi> yet ſure I am their <hi>fountaines</hi> are ſealed vp: <hi>The Nobles</hi> (as <note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 14.3. <hi>Iuel. Apolog.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ieremy</hi> complaines) <hi>haue ſent their ſeruants to the water, who came to the welles, but returned with their veſſels empty:</hi> which may more iuſtly conſtraine vs to remoue from <hi>Rome,</hi> then the failing of the Conduits compelled the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Romanes,</hi> to deſcend from the <hi>ſeauen hils</hi> and inhabite the Plaine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 6.68.</note>Our <hi>Church</hi> hath the words of eternall life, whither then ſhall we goe? It is the <hi>Arke</hi> of <hi>Noah,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine</hi> of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of our <hi>Sauiour, producing</hi> a fruitful progeny, <hi>reducing</hi> many fruitleſſe <hi>run-agates,</hi> many <hi>renegates,</hi> as here <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> who being conuerted turnes vnto the Lord by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7166:14"/>
prayer. <hi>Hee prayed to the Lord his God.</hi> And thus much of the <hi>Agent, [Hee.]</hi> Now followes the <hi>Action, [Prayed.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto you haue ſeene <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> not with <hi>Lots</hi> wife,<note place="margin">2. The Action. Gen. 19.26.</note> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>sform'd into a pillar of Salt, but with the Poets<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Amphion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> wife.</note> 
               <hi>Niobe,</hi> into a weeping and waimenting ſtone: now ſhall you ſee him with an humble and lowly heart, raiſing his ruined ſoule, <hi>depreſt</hi> with ſinne, <hi>deproſtrate</hi> for ſinne; lifting vp his <hi>bleared</hi> eyes, <hi>ſtreaming</hi> with teares, <hi>ſwelling</hi> for ſorrow: you ſhall ſee him <hi>rooſe</hi> vp the one, and <hi>raiſe</hi> vp the other, from the <hi>centre</hi> of the circled earth, beyond the <hi>circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> of the heauens.</p>
            <p>Behold therefore this penitent <hi>Publican</hi> on bended <hi>knees</hi> with a broken heart, behold his hands beating and thumping his flinty and obdurate <hi>breſt:</hi> looke well vpon this huge <hi>Whale,</hi> as one ſtiles that <hi>Whipſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Worſhip.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. behold in him a modeſt boldneſſe, and bold modeſtie, an acting paſſion, and a paſſionate action; looke into the grates of the <hi>Priſon</hi> and you ſhall find him <hi>praying:</hi> euen him who had <hi>tired</hi> himſelfe in purſuing <hi>vanity,</hi> and <hi>attired</hi> himſelfe, not with <hi>Tertullians</hi> Chriſtian-like <hi>cloake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tert. lib. de pall.</hi> Rom. 13.14. Reu. 6.11. Gen. 37.31.</note> Saint <hi>Pauls wedding Garment,</hi> or Saint <hi>Iohns White robes,</hi> but with <hi>Ioſephs Parti-coloured coate</hi> beſmear'd with blood: euen him ſhall ye find <hi>retiring</hi> to God by <hi>praire,</hi> with <hi>cheeks</hi> impearl'd with <hi>teares,</hi> with <hi>hands</hi> wringing for <hi>ſorrow,</hi> with an heart rieuing with <hi>ſighs,</hi> with a <hi>breaſt</hi> breaking with <hi>ſobs,</hi> for hee, hee it is that prayed: <hi>He tooke vnto him words,</hi> as the <hi>Lord</hi> exhorted <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Hoſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.3. Iſa. 38.14.</note> hee turned to his <hi>God</hi> with his father <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> he <hi>chattered</hi> like a <hi>Crane,</hi> he <hi>mourned</hi> like a <hi>Doue,</hi> and fixing his <hi>eyes</hi> vpon <hi>Heauen,</hi> that <hi>Starre-ſpangled Canopy,</hi> hee poured out a <hi>torrent</hi> of melodious <hi>Harmony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I liſt not here largely to dilate vpon the <hi>definition</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> of <hi>praire,</hi> whether it bee an <hi>eleuation</hi> of the <hi>mind</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>one:</hi> whether it be a <hi>communication</hi> of man with <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Caluin:</hi> whether it be either of theſe, or both theſe.<note place="margin">Caluin. Inſtit.</note> Nor need I <hi>macerate</hi> my ſelfe about the <hi>diſtribution</hi> of <hi>praire,</hi> bleſſed Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath exquiſitely and excellently
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7166:15"/>
expreſſed the <hi>kinds</hi> thereof,<note place="margin">1 Tim 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>Firſt, there bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>deprecations</hi> againſt euils to bee auoided.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Secondly, there be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>petitions</hi> for good things to be obtained.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Thirdly, there bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Interceſſions</hi> for others, to whom we are obliged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Fourthly, there be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>thanksgiuings,</hi> for the auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>euils,</hi> the obtaining of <hi>benefits</hi> by our ſelues or others. I dwell not in theſe, but poſt on to this <hi>propoſition,</hi> extracted from the propounded patterne of this our <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> namely,</p>
            <p>That <hi>it is the conſtant practiſe of euery penitent conuert, to poure out his</hi> prayers <hi>to prefer his</hi> Petitions, <hi>to ſend vp his</hi> ſuites <hi>and</hi> ſupplications <hi>to his God</hi> Let <hi>Ananias</hi> ſeeke in the houſe of <hi>Iudas</hi> after <hi>Saul</hi> of <hi>Tarſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 9.11.</note> and behold, hee ſhall finde him <hi>praying, Act.</hi> 9. Heare you not the <hi>Pythagori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> harmony of reuerting <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſounding ſo ſhrilly their <hi>De profundis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 130.1.</note> 
               <hi>Out of the depths haue I cried vnto thee O Lord? Pſal.</hi> 130. And ſurely,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſa. <hi>130.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>valdè in profundo ſunt, qui nec cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant de profundo,</hi> as ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> Thoſe are ſtifeled in the depths, who cry not out of the depths. A Tennis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball <hi>percuſſus ſurgit,</hi> the harder you ſtrike it, the higher it rebounds: The Lords obedient children, the <hi>harſhlier</hi> they be <hi>intreated,</hi> the <hi>heartilier</hi> they <hi>intreat</hi> and ſue for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:<note place="margin">Ier. 29.12.</note> ſtiffe necked <hi>Iſrael,</hi> being humbled by the yoke of <hi>Babel, Shall goe and cry and pray vnto their God, Ier.</hi> 29. Therefore ſhall euery one that is godly make his prayer vnto thee O God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.6.</note> ſurely in the flouds of great waters, then, euen then ſhall they come neare thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9.1.</note>But, oh that my <hi>head</hi> was full of <hi>water,</hi> and mine <hi>eyes</hi> two fountaines of <hi>teares,</hi> that I might weepe day and night, for the <hi>neglect,</hi> for the contempt of this <hi>duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are either <hi>tongue-tyed,</hi> or which is worſe, poſſeſt with a <hi>dumbe diuell?</hi> they are not able, or not deſirous, obſequiouſly to <hi>implore</hi> the all-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing <hi>power,</hi> the <hi>powerfull</hi> preſence of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:7166:15"/>
It is a legall veritie, that if the Child did neuer cry, it was neuer the Kings Subiect, it was neuer capable of any right, of any inheritance: yet (ſee their palpable abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) theſe <hi>dumbe men</hi> thinke to get in poſſeſſion the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full land of celeſtiall <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Turkes</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count dumbe men <hi>Santones,</hi> that is, Saints. Mr. <hi>Will. Bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulph.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Turkes</hi> may canonize their <hi>Dumbe-men</hi> for <hi>Saints</hi> or <hi>Santones,</hi> but ſure we are, theſe are incarnate Diuels.</p>
            <p>Others there be who pleade <hi>ſimplicitie,</hi> their vnpoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rudeneſſe, makes them that they dare not preſſe into Gods awefull preſence! But <hi>neceſſitas docet artes,</hi> extreame <hi>exigencie,</hi> will make the dumbe man ſpeake moſt <hi>eloquent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> Euen ruſticke clownes will play the Rhetoricians, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſtarue for bread.</p>
            <p>A third ſort there are, with whom God can neuer be <hi>acquainted,</hi> but in their <hi>extremities:</hi> ſuch as are the <hi>Cim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brians,</hi> who hold their idols in account, onely when they are encountred with a tempeſt. When <hi>Sheth</hi> had cauſe to call the name of his ſonne <hi>Enoſh,</hi> ſorrowfull <hi>Enoſh,</hi> then men begunne with alacritie to call vpon the Name of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah,</hi> Gen. 4. When Iſrael is in <hi>bondage,</hi> then are they <hi>free</hi> of ſpeech, <hi>Ex.</hi> 2. <hi>They ſighed and cryed for their oppreſſing ſlauerie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 2.23.</note> When <hi>Amalck</hi> comes to skirmiſh with the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 17.11.</note> then looke for <hi>Moſeſſes</hi> hand to be held vp Theſe <hi>Ionah-like, ſleepe</hi> in the ſhippe,<note place="margin">Ion. 1.5. with 2 2.</note> but <hi>pray</hi> in the Whales belly.</p>
            <p>But did you neuer heare of a horrid, and ſtrange miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen monſter, called the Chriſtian <hi>Atheiſt?</hi> he poſts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this duty of <hi>praire</hi> to the <hi>Prieſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.13. 2. Chro. 26 16</note> they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they ſerue at the Altar, and he with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> will nor vſurpe the <hi>Prieſts</hi> office. Hee may fetch his deſcent as farre as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> who would not trouble himſelfe to call vpon <hi>God,</hi> but intreates ſo much fauour of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Orate vos, pray yee vnto the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 9.28.</note> Exod. 9. He is ſomething allied to <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> who <hi>beſought</hi> that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet whoſe blood he <hi>ſought,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>to pray vnto the Lord and make interceſſion for him,</hi> King. 1.13. Had I not ſtyled him a <hi>Chriſtian Atheiſt,</hi> I might haue called him an <hi>Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7166:16"/>
lew:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abba Saul lib. Sanhed. cap. Helec. ex San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erdo De Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſu. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> for like at the <hi>Iewes</hi> will not ſuffer that Name of <hi>God Iehouah</hi> to be pronounced, but onely of the <hi>high Prieſt,</hi> and that onely <hi>once</hi> in the yeare, when he enters the <hi>Holyeſt of Holyes;</hi> ſo theſe; but I ſpare to apply it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Vnamque ab illis horam ad orandum, &amp;c. Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccl. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> begd one houre of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors to ſpend in <hi>praire,</hi> but we will not redeeme our dayes, our weekes, our moneths, our yeares from vanitie, to <hi>imploy</hi> them, in <hi>deploring</hi> our ſinnes, in <hi>imploring</hi> the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of our God. If euery one was forc'd to publiſh to the view of the vulgar, a Chronologicall hiſtorie, an hiſtoricall Chronologie of their owne exploits, then ſhould we ſee to the ſhame of <hi>mortals,</hi> how ſhameleſly we ſhuffle off our <hi>mortall</hi> dayes. So much time ſpent in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>hunting,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vir qui vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus magis, quàm orationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vacabat: de Iohan. <hi>13.</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranza in Sum. vit. Pontif.</note> ſayes our voluptuous <hi>Eſaw.</hi> So much time ſpent in <hi>courting</hi> our <hi>Delilahs,</hi> ſayes our amorous <hi>Sampſon.</hi> So much time ſpent in <hi>coffering Mammon,</hi> ſayes our auaricious <hi>Nabal.</hi> So much time ſpent in <hi>painting</hi> our <hi>faces,</hi> and <hi>ſteeling</hi> our <hi>foreheads,</hi> ſayes our gorgeous <hi>Iezabel.</hi> So much time ſpent in <hi>gormandizing,</hi> ſayes our licencious <hi>Libertine.</hi> So much time ſpent in <hi>quaffing</hi> and <hi>carouſing,</hi> ſayes our barbarous <hi>Scythian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scythia</hi> bred not one lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sage, ſaue onely <hi>Anachar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</hi> For as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance in wine is a whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to the wit, ſo exceſſe, is a mill-ſtone to it.</note> So much time ſpent in <hi>gaming,</hi> in <hi>carding</hi> and in <hi>dicing,</hi> ſayes our penurious <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall,</hi> but ſo little, ſo none in <hi>praying,</hi> ſo little, ſo none in <hi>calling</hi> vpon God.<note n="a" place="margin">Tully Orat. <hi>in</hi> Catilinam.</note> 
               <hi>O tempora, ô mores,</hi> Oh the <hi>times</hi> that we are fallen into, Oh the <hi>manners</hi> of men, or rather of bruitiſh beaſts, of men more bruitiſh then beaſts, then<note n="*" place="margin">Nu. 22.28.30.</note> 
               <hi>Balaams Aſſe,</hi> for <hi>ſhe ſpake twiſe to her Maiſter</hi> in one day, but theſe will not bid their <hi>God</hi> good <hi>morrow</hi> or good <hi>euen,</hi> though<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 17 27.</note> 
               <hi>by groping after him they might haue found him,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> once beſpoke his ſchoold <hi>Athenians,</hi> Act. 17.27.</p>
            <p>I could ſuggeſt vnto theſe, that rare and admirable are the <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>prayer:</hi> if we looke vpon the <hi>elements, prayer</hi> is a <hi>controuler,</hi> if we look vp into the <hi>heauens, prayer</hi> is a <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Eſt oratio vis Deo grata,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> a <hi>gracious prayer,</hi> is the moſt <hi>gratefull</hi> violence we can offer to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 1.10.12</note> 
               <hi>Eliaſſes prayer</hi> can fetch downe <hi>Fire</hi> from heauen,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7166:16"/>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.18.</note> 
               <hi>Samuels praier</hi> can cauſe the <hi>Aër</hi> to thunder,<note n="d" place="margin">Exod 15.25.</note> 
               <hi>Moſeſſes praier</hi> can ſweeten the embittred <hi>waters,</hi> the<note n="e" place="margin">Acts 4.31.</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtles prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> can ſhake the center of the ſenſeleſſe <hi>earth.</hi> At<note n="f" place="margin">Ioſh. 10 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſhuahs praier</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> muſt ſtay in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> and the <hi>Moone</hi> in the valley of <hi>Aialon.</hi> It climbes the battlements of <hi>Olympus,</hi> and with<note n="g" place="margin">Ge. 22.24.26.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtles with <hi>God</hi> till it get a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Socrat. hiſtor. Eccleſ l. <hi>5.</hi> c <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theodoſius</hi> obtained that victory againſt <hi>Eugenius,</hi> not by his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>proweſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Praeparatur ad bellum non tam telorum quàm orationum ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dij<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de Theodoſio Ruffians Hiſt. Eccleſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>33.</hi> Tam in pace qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in bello diuinum anxilium ſemper pelijt Theodoſuis, &amp; nunquam illo frauderetur. Theodorit. Hiſt. Eccleſ. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> but by <hi>powring</hi> out his <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> to the <hi>Lord</hi> of hoſtes.<note n="i" place="margin">Ferunt fulmen ſubſequutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quod hoſtes in exitium impulerit, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brem ad refocil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exercitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Euſeb. hiſt. Eccl. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> When the Campe of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aurelius</hi> was oppreſt with thirſt, the Chriſtian Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours by <hi>prayer</hi> obtained, not onely a <hi>ſhower</hi> to <hi>refreſh</hi> the <hi>Army,</hi> but <hi>thunder</hi> alſo to affringht the <hi>Enemie.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Horat.</note> 
               <hi>Sed quid terras alio calentes ſole mutamus?</hi> Why doe wee wade into a world of <hi>wonders,</hi> to finde out the <hi>wonderments</hi> wrought by <hi>prayer?</hi> it reſcued <hi>Manaſſes</hi> from the <hi>iawes</hi> of Hell, and reſtored <hi>Manaſſes</hi> to the ioyes of Heauen; for not S. <hi>Peter</hi> with his <hi>croſſe keyes,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the <hi>key</hi> of his <hi>croſſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Manaſſes</hi> with the <hi>key</hi> of his <hi>prayer,</hi> made paſſage to the Throne of Grace: <hi>He prayed to the Lord his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>deſire</hi> challenge our attention, to the third <hi>member</hi> of our preſent <hi>diuiſion,</hi> which is the <hi>Obiect</hi> of the <hi>Action, [Iehovah] the Lord.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Chryſ. hom. de Priſc. &amp; Aquila, ſiue de colendis Sacerdotibus.</note> 
               <hi>Studioſos arbritror ne laturos,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome, vt verbulum aliquod in ſacris libris, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptim praetereatur.</hi> Chriſt ſaies that the leaſt <hi>Iota,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that the leaſt <hi>Hebrew point ſhall neuer fade till all be fulfilled,</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 5.18. Luke 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. Here therefore I might play the <hi>Rabbin,</hi> and giue a reaſon why the <hi>great name</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as here in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſo almoſt in all tongues,<note n="*" place="margin">3 The Obiect.</note> it is wrttten onely with foure letters: the <hi>Aegyptians, Thewt;</hi> the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians Syros;</hi> the <hi>Arabians Alla;</hi> the <hi>French Dieu;</hi> the <hi>Germanes Gott;</hi> the <hi>Iewes</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iehouah</hi> in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew is written with foure Letters.</note> 
               <hi>Iehovah;</hi> to import that in the <hi>foure parts</hi> of the world his <hi>name</hi> is knowne, and that hee hath his Church in euery quarter.</p>
            <p>And here might I deplore the dangerous dotage of<note n="e" place="margin">Multos deos Manichaeus colendos eſſe admonet. Socrat. hiſt. Eccl. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>22.</hi> Duos affirmauit eſſe deos. Clemens Recog. lib. <hi>3. Which opinion went currant almoſt three hundred yeares, as</hi> Nicephorus <hi>writeth:</hi> Niceph. Eccel. Hiſtor. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:7166:17"/>
who multiply their <hi>Idols</hi> according to the <hi>Idaeas</hi> of their ſeduced phanſies. In <hi>Calicute</hi> they adore the <hi>diuel;</hi> In <hi>Perſia,</hi> their <hi>King:</hi> In <hi>Aegypt,</hi> the <hi>Crocodile:</hi> In <hi>Siam,</hi> a Prouince of <hi>India,</hi> they worſhip the higher <hi>Elements.</hi> The <hi>Magi</hi> worſhipt the <hi>Sunne,</hi> the <hi>Ophitae,</hi> the <hi>Serpent;</hi> the <hi>Petilianiſts, Iudas!</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> honour the <hi>whip</hi> that ſcourged, the <hi>Speare</hi> that pierced, the <hi>Nayles</hi> that faſtned, the <hi>Souldiour</hi> that goared our Sauious ſide.<note n="*" place="margin">Danaeus in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat. Orat. Dominicae.</note> 
               <hi>Danaeus</hi> dares to ſay, that <hi>Vna cum Rocho, canem; cum Ioſepho, Aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num; cum Agnete, agnum quoque colunt:</hi> That together with Saint <hi>Roch</hi> they worſhip a <hi>Dogge,</hi> together with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> they worſhip an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> and together with S. <hi>Agnes</hi> they worſhip a <hi>Lambe.</hi> According to the number of thy Countries are thy gods, O <hi>Babylon!</hi> S. <hi>George</hi> for <hi>England,</hi> S. <hi>Iames</hi> for <hi>Spaine,</hi> S. <hi>Denice</hi> for <hi>France,</hi> S. <hi>Patricke</hi> for <hi>Ireland.</hi> And as they make them <hi>Patrons</hi> for Kingdomes, ſo they create them <hi>protectors</hi> from <hi>diſeaſes,</hi> from <hi>diſaſters:</hi> The bleſſed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin,</hi> from <hi>Ship-wracke;</hi> S. <hi>Roch,</hi> from the <hi>peſtilence; Raphael,</hi> from <hi>ſore eyes; Apollonia,</hi> from the <hi>tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach.</hi> They <hi>worſhip</hi> for <hi>Saints</hi> ſuch as neuer were <hi>men,</hi> as <hi>ſuppoſititious Chriſtopher;</hi> or ſuch as were the worſt of men, as <hi>treacherous</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Inter Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros Pariſienſes quaeſtio erat, Damnatúſne ſit, an ſeruatus Bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettus. Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rf.</note> 
               <hi>Becket.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer hath the higheſt pitch of our <hi>affections,</hi> that is our God.<note n="a" place="margin">Auarus colit Mammona, &amp; Haereticus dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma quod finxit. —Vertunt in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Hier.</note> 
               <hi>Haereticus colit dogma quod finxit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierome: the Hereticke deifies the defied popularity of his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Midas</hi> worſhips his <hi>Mammon,</hi> that god of <hi>ruſt,</hi> who like a <hi>cancred god</hi> at laſt will conſume him. They ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus; Lais</hi> at <hi>Corinth; Mahomet</hi> at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople; Antichriſt</hi> at <hi>Rome; Machiauel</hi> at <hi>Florence; Arius</hi> at <hi>Alexandria; Aerius</hi> at <hi>Pontus;</hi> All theſe at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here alſo might I mightily torment the tortured <hi>Ghoſt</hi> of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> whoſe Statue pointed, <hi>Simoni deo ſancto:</hi> the <hi>Ghoſt</hi> of<note n="b" place="margin">Who yet in ſleepe and luſt perceiued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee a meere <hi>animal.</hi> Yea, though li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing he affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be ſtiled a god, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, he could not get a graue to burie him in, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Olympias</hi> lamentation in <hi>Eraſmus: ô fili; tu qui ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debas coeli parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps eſſe, huc toto impetu propera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; ne iis quidem potiri valuiſti, quae ſunt morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium omnium communia, terra ac ſepultura. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſ. Apophl. li.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>great,</hi> that <hi>great</hi> deſirer to be ſtil'd a <hi>god:</hi> But with<note n="c" place="margin">1 King. 22.31.</note> 
               <hi>Arams</hi> Captaines, I will fight neither with great nor ſmall, ſaue onely againſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the King of the bottomleſſe <hi>Abyſſe,</hi> the prophane zeale-ſcoffing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7166:17"/>
               <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> that black bratt of fathomleſſe perdition, brauing the <hi>Deity</hi> with a brazen brow.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Nulla eſt tam barbara natio, nulla gens tam efferata, cui non inſideat haec per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſio, Deum eſſe. Cicero de natur. Deorum. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Neuer was there Nation ſo rude and barbarous,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tully, but hath been perſwaded that there is a God.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Orpheus</hi> liued about that time in which <hi>Ehud</hi> and <hi>Shamgar</hi> iudged Iſrael, <hi>More Chronol.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Orpheus</hi> (that I may point at ſome of their learnedſt Sages) confeſſed that there was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>one begotten of himſelfe, by whom all things were made.</hi> Their ancient deſcription of a <hi>principle</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees only to God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaid that ancient Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, the firſt <hi>Principle</hi> is made of nothing. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaid <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> it is without generation! The ſame <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> is commended by<note n="c" place="margin">Ariſt. de Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> for that hee held that there was an <hi>immixt &amp; moſt ſimple vnderſtanding, which knew all things:</hi> whence the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> cald him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Seer</hi> and <hi>Beholder</hi> of all things whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the audacious <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> with a brazen &amp; iron forehead, blaſphemouſly<note n="d" place="margin">Pſa. 14.1. and 10.4. and 53.1.</note> ſaies in his heart <hi>There is no God,</hi> holding the Scriptures to be but fables, <hi>coyned</hi> for <hi>current</hi> onely to awe the world, I will, though very briefly, proue that there is a <hi>Iehouah</hi> to whom <hi>Manaſſes</hi> prayed, <hi>[Hee prayed to the Lord his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>excellency</hi> of the <hi>Angelicall nature</hi> ſhewes that it muſt proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>more excellent cauſe</hi> then is it ſelfe. Theſe heauenly <hi>Hïerarchies</hi> could not compoſe or frame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, therefore were they formed of ſome other cauſe, which muſt needes ſurpaſſe them in dignity, according that receiued <hi>Maxime</hi> in the <hi>Schoole, Propter quod vnum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt tale, illud ipſum eſt magis tale: That which giues ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency to another, muſt needs in it ſelfe be farre more excellent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, thoſe <hi>Heroïcall inſtincts</hi> in the minde of man, whereby extraordinarily great <hi>exploits</hi> haue beene atchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, muſt needes euince, that ſome <hi>ſuperiour power</hi> hath proſpered theſe vndertakings, and produced them to their ſeuerall iſſues and euents. How could eyther the pupill <hi>Aexander,</hi> ſo ſpeedily haue ouer-runne the world, with his warre-like, and more then <hi>Tragicall Tropheis?</hi> or his Tutor <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſo ſucceſſefully ſounded the depth of ſo many <hi>Arts,</hi> and poliſhed ſo many <hi>Sciences,</hi> had not ſome <hi>higher</hi> and <hi>more powerfull</hi> hand ayded them in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7166:18"/>
the accompliſhing of thoſe waighty enterpriſes?</p>
            <p>To ſpeake of the latter.<note n="*" place="margin">Entis à primo Actus eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> primi entis <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Is not the whole <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Arts,</hi> the energeticall and operatiue wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the firſt <hi>Beeing?</hi> Doth it not as <hi>firſtly</hi> ſpring and ariſe from him, ſo <hi>laſtly returne</hi> and <hi>retire</hi> to him againe? Herein like the leſſer riuers, which as they receiue their particular currents from the <hi>Maine,</hi> ſo doe they at length repay their due tribute to the <hi>Deepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider that if ſome <hi>Infinite Beeing</hi> bee not the repoſe and centre of our mindes, wee are all like <hi>toyling Leanders</hi> in the <hi>boyling Helleſpont,</hi> eaſeleſſe, reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, wretchleſſe, a very burthen to our ſelues, neuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with any terrene, or tranſient, or triuiall content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wee are all ſicke of a direfull dropſie, like <hi>ſelfe-ſoothing Narciſſus,</hi> of whom the Poet,
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Ouid.</note>
                  <l>Dumque ſitim ſedare cupit, ſitis altera creuit:</l>
                  <l>In vaine <hi>Narciſſus</hi> ſeekes to quench his thirſt,</l>
                  <l>Sith it was leſſe inſatiate at the firſt.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If with <hi>Alexander</hi> wee could neuer ſo ſucceſſefully ſubdue the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſe,</hi> yet with <hi>Alexander</hi> mounted on the Stage of encroaching arrogance, wee would burſt-forth into bitter teares, grieuouſly lamenting that there remaines not yet another world for vs to conquer.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, looke vpon thoſe <hi>horrors</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which ceaze vpon the <hi>mighty</hi> men of the earth, though in regard of their ſupereminent place, their eminent pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, their puiſſance, their proweſſe, their proſperous euents, they need not once ſhrinke at feare 'mid chiefeſt brunts of battle. Is not this then ſome ſuperiour <hi>Iudge,</hi> who thus makes them <hi>vaile</hi> the glory of their <hi>vanting</hi> plumes? Is not this ſome ſuperiour <hi>Power,</hi> who ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them their hainous guilt, thus dolefully diſmayes their dauntleſſe mindes? And to conclude, is not this ſome ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour <hi>Potentate,</hi> who declaring his dreadfull ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, thus heralds vnto them Deaths pale and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling triumphs?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 52.</note>Witneſſe <hi>Belchazzar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> behold him well, and whuiſhtly view his feature, he cannot keepe his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7166:18"/>
but is like vnto the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Diana</hi> in the Iland <hi>Chios,</hi> which on the one ſide being looked vpon ſeem'd to <hi>ſmile,</hi> but on the other to <hi>frowne:</hi> So hath he two faces, the one ſweld like <hi>Aeolus,</hi> and puft vp with drinking Wine; the other aſhy-pale and meager, with looking at the <hi>hand-writing</hi> on the wall. Pale trembling Coward,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.5.</note> what need'ſt thou feare? why is thy countenance chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, thy thoughts troubled,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.6.</note> the ioynts of thy loynes loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? why doe thy knees ſmite one againſt another? what? blurring and crying to ſee the Palme of a hand?<note place="margin">Dan. 5.7.</note> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man the former power of thy martiall arme, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou art guarded with a thouſand of thy Princes. See, here is plenty of the <hi>Red liquor</hi> of the <hi>grape,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.1.</note> which is like <hi>lapis Alchymicus,</hi> the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> conuerting a <hi>leaden paſſion</hi> into a <hi>golden,</hi> ſweet, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>contemplation.</hi> But of all theſe hee might truely ſay as <hi>Iob</hi> once ſpake of his Friends,<note place="margin">Iob. 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>Miſerable comforters are yee all!</hi> For indeede,<note place="margin">Iob. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>the arrowes of the Almighty are in him, and the terrours of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>yea changes and armies of ſorrowes doe fight againſt him.</hi> Now be it ſpoken vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee O King, that there is a King of Kings, that the Lord is a man of warre, his name is <hi>Iehouah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 5.3.</note> Hee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thy darts as ſtraw,<note place="margin">Iob. 41.20. Iob. 12.18. Iob. 12.21.</note> and laugheth at the ſhaking of the ſpeare: he looſeth the collar of Kings, and guir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth their loynes with a girdle. Hee powreth contempt vpon Princes, and maketh the ſtrength of the mighty weake. What ſhould I ſpeake of that common contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of God <hi>Caligula?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qui Deos tanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere contemne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, ad minima tonitrua &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura conniuere, caput ohuoluere, ad vero maiora, proripere ſe à ſtrato, ſub lectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que condere ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Sueton. in Caligul. cap. <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> who notwithſtanding would <hi>winke at the leaſt lightning, and couer his head.</hi> I will not now diſeaſe this timerous <hi>Tyrant,</hi> who creepes vnder the <hi>bed,</hi> and runnes into a <hi>benchhole,</hi> hoping ſo to eſcape from heauens reuenge-full thunder.</p>
            <p>Shall I ſumme vp all in a word? then thus. There muſt needs be ſome <hi>ouer-ruling Deitie,</hi> eſtabliſhing all rule and regencie. There muſt needs be ſome <hi>thought-ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſuperior Iudge,</hi> puniſhing the mighty <hi>Nimrods,</hi> the <hi>Gods</hi> of the earth. There muſt needs be ſome <hi>Infinite Beeing,</hi> ſatisfying the vaſt minds of vs mortals. There
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7166:19"/>
muſt needs be ſome <hi>ſupreme power,</hi> proſpering all <hi>high</hi> and <hi>heroicall euents.</hi> There muſt needs be ſome <hi>excellent cauſe</hi> of the <hi>Angelicall nature,</hi> ſurpaſſing in <hi>excellencie</hi> the <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie</hi> of them, who <hi>excell</hi> in <hi>excellencie</hi> all leſſe <hi>excellent</hi> creatures. This ouer-ruling <hi>Deity,</hi> this ſuperior <hi>Iudge,</hi> this infinite <hi>Beeing,</hi> this ſupreme <hi>power,</hi> this firſt and excellent <hi>cauſe</hi> is no other, can be no other then a <hi>God,</hi> than <hi>this God</hi> to whom <hi>Manaſſes prayed: Hee prayed to the Lord his God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solus Deus ipſe, quoad ſe, ſeip ſum nouit,</hi> God onely know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe, as inhabiting <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a light vnapproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, vnacceſſible,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.<note n="b" place="margin">Cicero de nat. Deorum.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> tels vs that <hi>Simonides</hi> after <hi>three daies</hi> ſtudy how to <hi>deſcribe God,</hi> was in the latter end more <hi>remote</hi> from any <hi>reſolution,</hi> then when he firſt began! See, here is <hi>Simonides,</hi> with the<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 19.11.</note> 
               <hi>Sodomites</hi> ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken blind, ſo that he is wearie with ſeeking the <hi>doore</hi> of this knowledge. And might not that ſo much to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired <hi>Aristotle,</hi> with<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>Elymas,</hi> goe about to ſeeke a man, to leade him by the hand! For to ſay as the truth is, the beſt <hi>Philoſopher</hi> is in this regard <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Juliam. in Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus.</note> as <hi>Iulian</hi> ſpoke of <hi>Traianus,</hi> vaunting of his Parthian tropheis before the gods; <hi>He is but as ſounding braſſe, or a tinkling Cymball.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.1.</note> The moſt renowned <hi>Orator</hi> attempting this, <hi>Verborum minutiis rerum frangit pondera,</hi> as <hi>one</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Seneca:</hi> He ſhould ſooner want a world, a <hi>Sea</hi> of words, then a <hi>drop</hi> of worthy matter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 33.23. Iob. 4.16.</note>Yet hath the <hi>Lord</hi> in mercy manifeſted vnto vs <hi>poſtica eius,</hi> his <hi>Backeparts, Exod.</hi> 33. So that as that <hi>Tyrian</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">— Caeteris in Orientem ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantibus, ſolus Occidentis regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem intuebatur. Iuſtin. Hiſtor. lib. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> proued in the end the wiſeſt, who concluding with his conſorts in the Euening, that hee who firſt could ſee the <hi>Sunne</hi> in the next enſuing morning ſhould be King, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked not toward the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> where firſt he ariſeth, but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>Weſt</hi> where his radiant rayes did firſt diſplay themſelues: So we, not being able to looke <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>face,</hi> at the reſplendent brightneſſe of whoſe glory, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Seraphims</hi> couered themſelues,<note n="*" place="margin">Eſa. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>Eſa.</hi> 6. muſt behold him as he himſelfe hath beene pleaſed to diſplay himſelfe vnto vs:<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 33.20. Ioh. 1.18. 1. Ioh. 4.12. Deut. 29.29. and 4.1. and 5.33. and 30.19.</note> 
               <hi>Further we may not ſee, &amp; liue; neither need we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7166:19"/>
ſee further, that we may liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Name of God <hi>Iehouah eſt nomen eſſentiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſſentia eſt qua per ſe, &amp; ex ſe abſoluté Deus eſt, &amp; exiſtit. Trelcat. Jnſtitut. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſayth <hi>Iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> a title typing out the <hi>eſſence</hi> of God vnto vs; nothing hath a <hi>Beeing</hi> but hee, nothing in compariſon of him. Excellently the Prophet <hi>Eſay, All nations before him, are as nothing, and they are counted to him leſſe then nothing,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Eſa. 40.17.</note> 
               <hi>Eſ.</hi> 40. Let not vs then poore wormes exalt our ſelues againſt this infinit <hi>Beeing:</hi> Let vs not dare to conceiue or ſpeake any thing which is vnworthy of ſo great a <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> ſeeing nothing can be ſpoken <hi>worthy</hi> of God, which is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>vnworthy,</hi> becauſe it may be ſpoken.</p>
            <p>We are now almoſt come aſhore ready to caſt anchor,<note place="margin">4. The Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Obiect.</note> for there remaineth onely the <hi>Application of the Obiect, [His God] Nonne ſi fluctuat fides, inanis eſt &amp; ſpes noſtra?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. in Epiſtol Cont. Abailard.</note> ſayth <hi>Bernard.</hi> It not that <hi>Academicall</hi> opinion of miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doubting, a <hi>doctrine</hi> full of <hi>danger?</hi> the <hi>Forge</hi> of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire?</hi> the <hi>Gulfe</hi> of <hi>hell?</hi> A poyſoning <hi>Brazuto?</hi> a ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing <hi>Ioab?</hi> A perfidious <hi>Catilin,</hi> noting vs with the eye, and deſigning vs all to the infernall vault of pitchie <hi>Acheron?</hi> yet ſee and wonder, the <hi>Councill</hi> of <hi>Trent defines</hi> it,<note place="margin">Concil. Trident. ſeſſ. <hi>6.</hi> can. <hi>12.</hi> Bellarm. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Iuſtif. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min defends</hi> it, to be an aſſertion, worthy to winne our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt reputation.</p>
            <p>Here could I wound them with their owne weapons; <hi>Sed ſatis eſt potuiſſe.</hi> O my ſoule, ſurceaſe with ſetled reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. If any of the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of the <hi>Prophets</hi> will here ſend to ſeeke <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> anſwere him with the tongue of men and Angels, <hi>quid quaeritis viuentem inter mortuos? Why ſeeke yee the liuing among the dead?</hi> Why ſeeke yee <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in the <hi>valley</hi> of <hi>Ben-hinnom?</hi> hee is aſcended into heauen, the <hi>valley</hi> of <hi>Viſion!</hi> Why ſeeke yee <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in the <hi>High-places?</hi> or rather why ſeeke yee not <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in the <hi>High-places?</hi> for <hi>ſurrexit,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Hee is aſcended into heauen, he is tranſported by the <hi>Angels</hi> into <hi>Abrahams bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</hi> He is entred into that figuratiue and myſticall <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> that <hi>pearleſſe</hi> place of <hi>endleſſe</hi> pleaſure, that ſacred <hi>Sanctuarie</hi> of a <hi>ſinner,</hi> that <hi>renowmed receptable</hi> of the ſoule, wherein he now enioyes eternall bliſſe.</p>
            <p>Hee hath abridg'd the way to heauen, and made a ſhort
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7166:20"/>
cutt to the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Canaan</hi> the Greekes call <hi>Phoenicia,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifies a palmetree, which was the ſpeciall cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of <hi>Phoeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> as is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in many old coynes which now are extant. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> for a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Iudaea,</hi> ſtamped vpon his coyne a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſitting with her backe to a palmetree, which this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>Iudaea Capta.</hi>
               </note> that land of <hi>Palmetrees,</hi> where carying triumphant <hi>palmes</hi> in his hands after many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts and tribulations, hee now keepes a continuall <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth,</hi> an endleſſe <hi>Halleluiah,</hi> an eternall <hi>Iubile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for you, my <hi>attentiue Auditors,</hi> let <hi>Manaſſes</hi> this day reade you a lecture, not of late but ſpeedy <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Of all that we poſſeſſe onely <hi>time</hi> is ours, and of all <hi>times</hi> onely the <hi>time</hi> preſent. <hi>Auſtin</hi> for the gaine of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worlds, would not be an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> for halfe an houre. <hi>Baſil</hi> to wade in wealth, would not <hi>preſume</hi> for halfe a moment. <hi>Baſiliſcus</hi> the <hi>Martyr</hi> to ſaue his life, would not <hi>recant</hi> for halfe a minute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tempus ſenex eſt, Time</hi> is Older then <hi>Methuſhelah,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 5.27.</note> he liued nine hundred ſixty and nine yeeres, yet then hee dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but <hi>time</hi> hath beene fiue thouſand yeares and yet he hath ſtill a being. <hi>Tempus ſenex eſt, Time</hi> is as ancient as the brighteſt <hi>Angel,</hi> yet is he like<note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>Aſahel,</hi> as light on foot as a wild Roe. <hi>Tempus ſenex eſt, Time</hi> is older then Natures <hi>fabricke,</hi> yet he weares a fore-top; but take heed, <hi>pòſt eſt occatio calua,</hi> hee is bald behind, take hold <hi>in time, time</hi> preſent is onely ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Security,</hi> ſinnes <hi>Circe,</hi> luls vs in the lappe of <hi>delight,</hi> and ſings a <hi>requiem</hi> to our ſoules: with<note n="c" place="margin">Suetonius.</note> 
               <hi>Suetoniuſſes Crow</hi> ſhe ſtands vpon the <hi>Capitoll</hi> and proclaimes an <hi>Omne bene,</hi> all will be well, though you repent hereafter. But the <hi>Lord</hi> with<note n="d" place="margin">Gellius.</note> 
               <hi>Socrates,</hi> that <hi>Athenian Eagle,</hi> lookes vpon <hi>this</hi> Sun. With <hi>Zachary,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Zach. 9.12.</note> 
               <hi>Hodie annuncians, to day he doth declare it,</hi> Turne you with <hi>Manaſſes.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſa. 95.7, 8. Heb. 3 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>To day</hi> then heare his voyce, and harden not your hearts as in the prouocation.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="g" place="margin">And thirty daies liberty he granted to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors, to paſſe betwixt the ſentence &amp; the execution, <hi>Vt intermedio tempore, ira Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ris nonni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil mitigaretur, et miſericordia locus aperiatur. Sozomen. Hiſt. Eccleſ. li.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note>
               <hi>Theodoſius</hi> gaue his foes <hi>ten dayes</hi> liberty, before hee ſhewed the leaſt extremity, but if theſe <hi>ten daies</hi> were <hi>tenne</hi> times multiplyed, there is not the leaſt here but hath had them offered. The Lord hath giuen vs time to <hi>turne,</hi> and we muſt <hi>returne</hi> a reckoning how we ſpend it. <hi>Omne te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus nobis impenſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requiritur à nobis qualiter ſit expenſum.</hi> But we with the euil <hi>ſeruant</hi> haue hid this talent in the Earth, with <hi>Pericles</hi> we doe not thinke ſo much to make vp our <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts,</hi> as how to make no <hi>reckoning</hi> vp at all. We ſay as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7166:20"/>
               <hi>Phocion</hi> ſayd vnto the <hi>Athenians, If Alexander be dead to day, he will be dead to morrow;</hi> If wee haue <hi>time</hi> to <hi>turne</hi> to day we ſhall haue <hi>time</hi> to <hi>returne</hi> to morrow.</p>
            <p>Thus is <hi>tempus duratio rerum,</hi> God doth giue vs <hi>time</hi> to <hi>turne,</hi> but wee are hardned in heart; wt will not <hi>turne.</hi> With <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> we weare the <hi>ſlow-ſliding Snaile</hi> vpon our Enſigne, ancompaſt in <hi>a mocking motto, Lentè festinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi> With <hi>Callipedes</hi> in <hi>Suetonius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suetonius.</note> We ſpend our daies in <hi>mouing,</hi> but goe not forward <hi>one cubit.</hi> We ſlug in ſloath, and languiſh in <hi>delight,</hi> wee giue our ſelues the raines of raging <hi>appetite;</hi> wee cut too faſt the triple front of <hi>Time,</hi> and thinke to repent as ſeriouſly as <hi>Manaſſes</hi> when wee liſt. But alas, our <hi>liues</hi> are not our owne <hi>fee-ſimple:</hi> our <hi>bodies</hi> are <hi>houſes,</hi> but of <hi>duſt: our ſelues</hi> are all but <hi>liuing clay;</hi> Our <hi>ſoules</hi> are <hi>tenants but all will;</hi> wee may not, wee muſt not promiſe to our ſelues a <hi>day.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> indeed is our <hi>Landlord,</hi> but we haue no leaſes of our liues. We <hi>grow</hi> like <hi>graſſe,</hi> in the morning we <hi>flouriſh,</hi> but in the euening <hi>fade</hi> away.<note place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note> 
               <hi>This night ſhall they fetch thy ſoule</hi> was <hi>Diueſſes</hi> doome. <hi>Mihi hodie, cras tibi; to me to day, to thee to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, is the dead mans dole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Non poteſt in morte videre vitam, qui non vult in vita prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidere mortem:</hi> If <hi>Sion</hi> will not <hi>repent</hi> while ſhe hath <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>England returne</hi> while grace is offered, <hi>Sion</hi> ſhall ſplit her heart with griefe, <hi>England</hi> ſhall mourne and not bee comforted: Her <hi>Cities,</hi> ſhall be waſted without inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and her houſes without a man.<note place="margin">Eſa. 13.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Zijm</hi> ſhall lodge within her <hi>Townes,</hi> her Temples ſhall be full of <hi>Ohim: Iim</hi> ſhall cry within her <hi>palaces, Dragons</hi> ſhall creep into her pleaſant <hi>places.</hi> For <hi>Nebo</hi> and for <hi>Dibon</hi> ſhall <hi>Moab</hi> howle,<note place="margin">Eſa. 15.2.</note> for <hi>Nebo</hi> and for <hi>Heſhbon</hi> ſhall <hi>Medeba</hi> weepe: <hi>Ieremies</hi> head ſhall <hi>flow</hi> with water, <hi>Eſayes</hi> eyes ſhall <hi>flood</hi> out teares, becauſe their people will not <hi>turne,</hi> becauſe they <hi>returne</hi> not in time with good <hi>Manaſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With good <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſeeing we returne not ſpeedily to the <hi>Lord,</hi> the Lord hath made our <hi>heauen braſs,</hi> &amp; our <hi>earth</hi> as <hi>iron.</hi> The <hi>Elements</hi> are vp in armes, and all the <hi>creatures</hi> turne our foes. The <hi>Fire</hi> deuowreth many houſes, and the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7166:21"/>
flame conſumeth many towns. The <hi>Aer</hi> hath beene infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the <hi>plague, peſtilence</hi> afflicted many people. The <hi>Water</hi> hath roar'd, and ſwel'd, and ouerwhelm'd the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt ground. The <hi>Earth</hi> hath quak't to view our vanity, and groanes to beare the burthen of our villany.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Turne</hi> therefore <hi>now</hi> ye houſe of <hi>Iſrael, turne</hi> you with <hi>Manaſſes</hi> from your euill wayes. Thinke not to <hi>conne</hi> the <hi>Pſalme of mercy,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Iudge</hi> of all <hi>fleſh,</hi> ſhall ride in <hi>circuit</hi> to put a <hi>period</hi> to thy daies, ſhall ſit in <hi>iudgement</hi> to cut ſhorter thy <hi>thred</hi> of life; but now while thou haſt <hi>time</hi> to <hi>turne, turne</hi> to God; <hi>turne</hi> to God <hi>à toto, à tanto, à tantillo;</hi> from <hi>all,</hi> from the <hi>leaſt,</hi> from the <hi>greateſt</hi> ſinnes, <hi>turne ſpeedily</hi> with <hi>Manaſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.3. &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>Thus</hi> if thou doeſt <hi>turne, bleſſed</hi> ſhalt thou be in <hi>City,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed</hi> in the <hi>towne. Bleſſed</hi> ſhall be the <hi>ſeed</hi> of thy body, &amp; the <hi>fruit</hi> of thy <hi>field. Bleſſed</hi> ſhall be the <hi>increaſe</hi> of thy <hi>kine,</hi> and the flocks of thy <hi>ſheepe.</hi> Thy <hi>land</hi> ſhall flow with <hi>milk</hi> and <hi>honey,</hi> and thou ſhalt <hi>waſh thy paths in butter.</hi> Thy <hi>rocks</hi> ſhall powre out oylie <hi>Riuers,</hi> and thou ſhalt <hi>waſh thy cloake in Wine.</hi> Thou ſhalt be <hi>bleſſed</hi> here on earth with <hi>great feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,</hi> and triumph with <hi>Manaſſes</hi> for all <hi>Eternity.</hi> Then ſhalt thou <hi>reigne</hi> in <hi>Heauen,</hi> where is <hi>Voluptas ſine moerore, tranquilitas ſine tremore, amoenitas ſine terrore:</hi> where is <hi>ioy</hi> without <hi>terrour, eaſe</hi> without <hi>dolour, health</hi> without <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</hi> Thou ſhalt <hi>reigne</hi> in <hi>Heauen, Cujus Rex eſt Veritas, Lex eſt Charitas, Pax eſt aequitas:</hi> Whoſe <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Verity,</hi> whoſe <hi>Law</hi> is <hi>Charity,</hi> whoſe <hi>Peace</hi> is <hi>Equity.</hi> To the which <hi>he</hi> bring vs, who, when we were <hi>loſt</hi> in ſinne with <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> ſo <hi>earely ſought</hi> vs; who, when we were <hi>ſold</hi> to ſinne with <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> ſo <hi>dearely</hi> bought vs, <hi>Ieſus,</hi> the <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Lambe</hi> of <hi>God, God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> the <hi>Man Chriſt Ieſus, God bleſſed</hi> for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Ternae &amp; aternae Trinitati, aſcribatur honor omnis, gloria, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, in ſaecula ſaeculorum.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Vox audita perit, litera ſcripta manet.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7166:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
